Do not use the flash to take pictures during the tour
進行中也請勿使用閃光燈拍照
Thank you for your cooperation
感謝您的配合
Also, what about the Academia Sinica?
另外 中央研究院這邊呢
We will also share the audio and video of the live broadcast of our past knowledge feast
也會將我們過往知識饗宴的直播的影音
put it on youtube
放到YouTube上面
So if everyone after the speech
所以大家如果在演講結束後
If you want to relive the essence of past speeches
想要再回味一下過往的演講精華的話
You can search Academia Sinica directly on YouTube
都可以直接上YouTube搜尋中央研究院
You can watch videos of our past speeches
就可以看到我們過往的演講的影片
Thanks
謝謝
Do not take photos with flash
請勿使用閃光燈拍照
instrument enrolled
instrum  enrolled
Hosted by Vice President Fu Dong
由福東副院長為我們主持
thank you
謝謝各位
Welcome and thank you for participating in this month's feast of knowledge
歡迎也謝謝各位參加這個月的知識饗宴
Our main award today is Pan Wenhan, a special review researcher
今天我們的主獎人是潘文涵特評研究員
Professor Pan Wenhan
潘文涵教授是孔內尉大學
Cornell University PhD in Nutritional Epidemiology
康奈尉大學是營養流行病學的博士
acquired in 1983
1983年得到的
He is at Northwestern University
他在西北大學
it's a north
這是一個北部
A Northwestern University
一個Northwestern University
Department of Community Health and Preventive Medicine
社區健康及預防醫學系
postdoctoral research
當人博士後研究
Returned to China in 1987
1987年回國
Into the service of Central Medical College
進到中央醫學院服務
Institute of Biomedical Sciences
在生物醫學科學研究所
He is now a special researcher at the firm
他現在是生意所的特別研究員
Dr. Pan's field of research
潘博士的研究領域
nutritional epidemiology
就是營養流行病學
His field of very distinguished research is
他在非常卓越的研究的領域是
Cardiovascular disease and nutrition
心臟血管疾病跟營養的關係
I think he will share this topic with us today
我想他今天會跟我們分享這個議題
has published more than 300 papers
是發表了超過300多篇的論文
He also received many awards
他也得到許多的獎項
Important awards include the 2004
重要的獎項包括2004年獲得
Outstanding Research Award from Taiwan Nutrition Society
臺灣營養學會頒發的傑出研究獎
Received Lifetime Achievement Award from Asia Pacific Society of Clinical Nutrition in 2010
2010年獲得亞太臨床營養學會終身成就獎
In 2015, he was awarded the Outstanding Contribution Award for Science and Technology by the Executive Yuan
2015年獲得行政院科學技術傑出貢獻獎
The last Executive Yuan is the Executive Yuan
這個最後行政院是行政院
One of the highest honors in academia
在學術界最高的一個榮譽
Alright then we welcome Professor Pan Wan now
好 那我們現在就歡迎潘婉教授
good night ladies and gentlemen
各位女士 各位先生晚安
first of all thank you very much
我首先非常謝謝
Thank you, Vice President Liu, for inviting me to the feast of knowledge
謝謝劉副院長邀請我來知識饗宴
Let me share with you today's topic
來跟大家來分享今天這個議題
Vice President Liu is actually my old officer.
劉副院長其實也是我的老長官
is the director of our Institute of Biomedical Sciences
就是我們生物醫學科學研究所的所長
So he recommended me to speak
所以他推薦要我來講的話
I also cherish such an opportunity very much.
我也是非常珍惜有這樣的一個機會
To be able to work with colleagues in our hospital
能夠和我們院裡面同仁
Or some friends from the community to talk about
或者是社區的一些朋友來談一下
Citation vitality eats out this topic
引法活力吃出來這個議題
This is a very important topic now
這個是現在非常重要的一個題目
because of medical advances
因為醫學的進步
the improvement of economic life
那經濟生活的改善
Now everyone pays more and more attention to health
現在大家越來越重視健康
So the elderly are very, very
所以就是高齡者非常的非常的
very many
數目非常的多
But what about some of the health problems encountered by old age?
但是高齡所碰到的一些健康的問題呢
actually some
其實都是一些
In other words, there is no way to go deep into the research.
怎麼說就是研究上還沒有辦法很深入
there are many things we don't know
還有很多的東西我們不知道的
I am very happy to talk about this topic today
今天很高興來談論一下這個題目
So today I mainly tell you about this content
那今天我主要跟大家講的這個內容
Layer these parts
分層這幾個部分
when i will start
那我會開始的時候
because we speak of vitality
因為我們講到活力
In fact, another aspect of vitality is weakness.
其實活力的另一個面向就是衰弱
how not to weaken
怎麼樣不衰弱
Maybe it's the other side of vitality
也可能就是活力的另外一面
So I'm going to tell you first
所以我先要跟大家講一下
incapacity
活力這個衰弱與失能
and the phenomenon of geriatric syndrome
以及老年症候群這個現象
so you might be clearer
所以你可能就會比較清楚
How can we make the Citing French family
怎麼樣能夠讓引法族的
still live with such vitality
還活出這樣一個活力來
That's another
那另外就是
For our comparison there may be some
針對我們比較可能有一些
What about the younger audience?
比較年輕的聽眾呢
I can learn about the aging process
我可以了解一下老化過程中
Changes in our bodies and our bodies
我們身體跟身體的改變
so maybe even middle age
所以甚至就是可能是中年
followed by young
後跟年輕
you can think at this time
你都可以在這個時候來思考
how do i keep healthy
我怎麼樣保健
So when I go to Citing the French
所以我以後到引法族的時候
I can be at my best
我能夠在一個最佳的狀態上
After understanding this
這樣了解之後呢
Maybe we'll be motivated
可能我們就會被motivate起來
there will be a motive
就會有一個動機
So what am I going to do?
要說那我到底要怎麼辦
to avoid such an aging process
來避免這樣一個老化過程
So I will talk about some of the main content of today
所以我下面就講到今天主要的一些內容
It's something related to frailty
就是和衰弱症相關的一些
Factors in a Nutritious Diet
營養飲食的因素
Of course I don't want to talk like a lecture
當然我不希望說像講課一樣
Everyone just listened to the textbook
教課書那大家光聽了說
should be like this should be like that
應該這樣應該那樣
so why do i say that
所以我為什麼會這樣講
Some of our empirical research
我們的一些實證研究
I will also introduce to you a little
也會跟大家稍微介紹一下
that apart from debility
那除了衰弱症以外
I'll talk a little bit about coercion
我會稍微談一下施制症
Because of weakness and restraint
因為衰弱跟施制
This is in geriatric syndrome
這是老年症候群裡面
most common most important
最常見的最重要的
So these nutrients
所以這個營養的這些
After this knowledge is introduced
這個知識介紹完畢之後
I'll tell you a little bit
我會跟大家稍微說一下
We are currently applying this knowledge to the community
我們目前把這樣的知識運用在社區
A few simple photos to tell everyone
簡單的幾張告訴大家
we have some community residents
我們在有一些社區居民
have begun to absorb this knowledge
已經開始在吸收這個知識
do something like this one
做一些這樣的一個
a practical operation
實務上的一個操作
ok that is
好那就是
Today's main content
今天的主要的內容
Finally, I will tell you
最後我也會跟大家講一下
Our Academia Sinica has an Academia Sinica nutrition information website
我們中央研究院的有一個中研營養資訊網
The information in the middle can be used by everyone
中間的資訊大家可以拿來運用
in myself and in my family
在自己的身上還有自己的家人的身上
Okay, what we're talking about today
好 那今天所講的東西
I also want to tell you
我也要跟大家說一下
A lot of the knowledge we talked about today
我們很多今天講的這個知識
It is because of a sustainable project of Academia Sinica
是因為進行了中央研究院的一個永續計畫
so some get some new knowledge
所以有一些得到一些新知
In addition, a lot of information is also from the National Health Service
另外很多的資料也是來自國民健康署
Some information from our Taiwan Nutrition and Health Survey
我們所做的台灣營養健康調查的一些資料
Allows us to do some data mining
能夠讓我們做一些資料的採礦
In the community care base just mentioned
在剛剛講到的這個社區關懷據點
We are already doing some dietary interventions
我們現在已經在做一些飲食的介入探討
That's because the nutritional status and dietary patterns of the elderly from the National Health Service
那是因為國健署的這個老年營養狀況及飲食型態
Correlation studies with various geriatric syndromes
與各種老年症候群的相關性研究
Then here are some of my partners
那這邊就是我的一些合作夥伴
A lot of what I'm talking about today is them with me
很多今天我講的東西都是他們跟我一起
made
做出來的
then first let me talk
那首先我就來談一下
Frailty and disability and geriatric syndrome
衰弱與失能以及老年症候群
Then let me tell you about us alone
那要先跟大家講一下我們一個人
How do we human beings enter a state of incapacity or weakness
我們人是怎麼樣進入一個失能或一個衰弱的一個狀態
And what is the relationship between disability and weakness?
而這個失能和衰弱是什麼樣的一個關係
I don't know if you can see this picture clearly
這個圖不曉得大家看不看得清楚
That is to say, we humans can divide it into
就是說我們人我們可以把它分成
Use this line to make a distinction
用這條線來做一個區分
This place is an old man's function index
這個地方是一個老人的功能指數
So when someone with your better function
所以在你功能比較好的一個人
If you face a small illness
如果你面對到一個小小的病痛的時候
your function may be reduced
你的功能可能有所下降
That's because he recovered from his illness and returned to health
那因為病好了又恢復了健康
But if our body is in a relatively weak state
但是如果說我們的身體是在處於一種相對比較衰弱的一個狀況下
I may have a cold, diarrhea or bad teeth
我可能碰到一個感冒、瀉度或者是牙齒不好的時候
Possibly the function will drop in a very short time
可能功能就會在很短的時間內下降
to a state where there may be no way to drop
到一個狀態可能沒有辦法下降
into a state of dependence
就進入了一個依賴的狀態
So everyone knows the geriatric syndrome we are talking about today
所以大家知道我們今天講的這個老年症候群
In fact, he is not a problem encountered by people in their fifties and sixties.
其實他並不是五六十歲的人所碰到的問題
but usually older
而是通常是更老
People in their seventies and eighties
七八十歲的人
that you have been very healthy all your life
就是你一生都非常健康
no cardiovascular disease
沒有心臟血管疾病
nothing sick
什麼病都沒有
a situation you will also encounter
你也會碰到的一個狀況
So is one such a reference method code by code
所以是一個這樣的一個引法逐碼
We're talking about something like this
我們講到的是這樣的一個問題
so that means
那所以就是說
One should try to maintain one's own function
一個人要盡量的維持自己的功能
is in good condition
是不錯的狀況
so you don't run into little ailments
所以你才不會再碰到一些小小的病痛
When challenged, it falls into a so-called
挑戰的時候就落入了所謂的一種
into a state of dependence
進到一種依賴的狀態
just dependent
就dependent
Then you have to rely on someone else's state
然後要依靠別人的一個狀態
Or lie in bed and never get up again
或者是臥床就再也起不來了
But how do we approach this issue?
但是我們要怎麼樣來看待這個問題呢
What about the picture I showed you here?
我這邊所給大家看到的這個圖呢
is a state that shows the aging of us alone
是顯示出我們一個人的老化的一個狀態
We are generally healthier people
我們一般比較健康的人
It is a gradual degeneration of function
他是逐漸的功能的退化
Then it must be maintained under a normal life
那它都要維持在一個常態生活下
probably such a very healthy energy
可能這樣的一個非常健康的能量
to very old age
到非常老的時候
it enters into a state of weakness
它才會進入一個衰弱的一個狀況
so that aging
以至於老化
What about the ones who sustain better?
那維持得更好的人呢
It's the red line that's always been level.
是這個紅線一直都保持水平的狀態
May be there are some very healthy people
可能到了有一些非常健康的人
to one hundred years old
到了一百歲
When I was over a hundred years old
一百多歲的時候呢
It is possible that this function line will suddenly drop
才會可能突然這條功能線下降
and then move on to the next stage of life
然後就走到人生的下一個階段
But what if a person with a lot of pain
但是如果一個病痛比較多的人呢
it follows the curve that tends to be
它走的是往往是這條曲線
That is to say, its functionality degrades rapidly
也就是說它的功能下降得很快
when it's not too old
它在不是太年紀大的時候
into a state of weakness
就進入了衰弱的狀態
So because it's in a weakened state
所以因為它在衰弱的狀態
It is easy to enter into incapacity
就很容易的就進入了失能
It's about reaching this final stage of life.
而就是走到人生的這個最終的一個階段
And so of course we want to say
而所以我們當然是希望說
to keep as much as possible
要盡可能的能夠保持
a state of robustness and vitality
一種健壯有活力的狀態
Then maintain the red line to the highest
然後在那個紅線呢維持到最高
don't then finally if it's going to fall
不要 然後最後如果要掉下來
also in the shortest possible time
也是在最短的時間內
fall down it's a so-called
掉下來 這是一個所謂的
Healthy
Healthy
That is to say, health and longevity
就是說健康長壽
means you can put your
就是說你能把你的
this time of life
人生的這個時間
maintain a peak
維持在一個最高峰的狀態
the longer the better
越久越好
Then if what is going to drop is in a very short time
那如果要掉落的是在很短時間內
If such a situation of falling
假如這樣子掉落的一個狀況
so aging
所以老化呢
aging process
老化這個過程
eventually debilitating
最終會引起衰弱
if you are in a debilitated state
如果你在一個衰弱的狀態之下
if any event occurs
如果有任何事件發生
The event can be a fall
這個事件可以是跌倒
Cold or crab belly or bad teeth
感冒或者蟹肚或者牙齒不好
What if you're in a debilitated state?
那如果你是處於一個衰弱的狀態的話呢
quickly become incapacitated and dependent
就很快的變成失能跟依賴
What about the topic we're talking about today?
那我們今天談論的這個議題呢
that's how
就是怎麼樣
let at a very old age
讓在年紀非常大的時候
To avoid such a situation from happening
能夠避免這樣的一個狀況的一個發生
So it's called
所以就是所謂的
such a state of vitality
引法活力的這樣的一個狀態
Then I just took this one
那我剛剛這一張
Let me show you that there is a line in this picture
給大家看到這張圖有一條線
That's when you say it's because of various reasons
就是當你如果說是因為各種原因
when young
年輕的時候
not taking good care of your body
沒有照顧好自己的身體
has entered a state of weakness
已經進入了衰弱的狀態
can you still reply
你是不是還能回復呢
actually it is possible
其實是可以的
which means you can still work hard
就是說你還是可以努力
let this one of yours
讓你的這一條
This function curve comes back up
這個功能曲線回到上面來
So it's definitely a possible situation
所以這絕對是一個可能的狀況
So we have bodies now
所以就是我們現在有身體
Don't be discouraged by those who rub a little
稍微擦的人也不要氣餒
can be used in some ways
可以用一些方式
Lifestyle Ways to Get You Back
生活型態的方式讓你回復
Then you walk in a
然後你又走在一個
Very good for a healthy one on the road
非常好的一個健康的一個道路上
Well, what I just talked about is
好 那我剛剛談到的是
because we talk about vitality
因為我們談活力
So we're talking about its inverse
所以我們就談到它的反向
weak
衰弱
Frailty and sarcopenia are two sides of the same coin
衰弱症跟肌少症是一體的兩面
I think many of you have heard of sarcopenia
我想大家很多人也聽過肌少症
basically means
基本上就是說
Sarcopenia is when your body
肌少症是當你的身體裡面的
This muscle mass gradually decreases
這個肌肉質量逐漸的減少
reduce
減少
But it may not have reached a critical point
但是可能還沒有到一個關鍵點
so you can function normally
所以你功能都可以正常
But in one case
但是到一個情況下
less muscle mass
肌肉量少到一個程度
Plus the quality of the muscle
再加上肌肉的質 品質
if bad again
如果又不好的時候
so-called debility
就會產生所謂的衰弱症
Frailty is often closely related to chronic disease
衰弱症常常和慢性病是息息相關的
I just talked about frailty and disability
那我剛剛講到衰弱症跟失能
may cause disability
可能會導致失能
Then if we look at some statistics
那我們如果看一些統計數字來看的話
If we look at the weakened group
如果我們看衰弱的這群人中間
Half of him has various so-called chronic diseases
一半他都有各式各樣的所謂的慢性病
As mentioned by our vice president just now, cardiovascular diseases and diabetes
像剛剛我們副院長提到心臟血管疾病 糖尿病
various diseases
各種這些病
Then these diseases will indeed cause the debility to occur earlier
那這些病確實會讓衰弱發生得比較早
One-fifth of the feeble
那衰弱的人中間有五分之一
One in five is also paired with disabilities and comorbidities
五分之一也搭配有失能以及共病
About 6% are disabled but have no comorbidities
大概6%是有失能 但是沒有共病
Almost one in four people with only frailty alone
單獨只有衰弱症的人差不多是四分之一
this is the situation
是這樣的狀況
So we can see that these conditions exist at the same time
所以我們可以看到這些狀況都是同時存在的
Then I will use the slide below to talk to you
那我就用下面這張slide來跟大家談一下
the health of the elderly
就是老年人的健康問題
What kind of problems do the elderly face?
老年人到底會碰到什麼樣的問題呢
It's not just the old people we often hear
它其實不只是我們常常聽到的老年人
Have high blood pressure, diabetes, hyperlipidemia, heart disease, stroke
有高血壓啦 有糖尿病啦 高血脂症啊 心臟病啊 中風
Uh, these are not just one question.
呃 這些不是光是這樣的一個問題啊
Let me explain to you from this diagram
那從這一個圖示我來給大家解釋一下
each of us will age
我們每一個人都會老化的
even if you don't have any disease
即便你沒有任何的疾病
You too are on an aging path
你也走在一個老化的道路中
Possibly due to physical damage from some free machines
可能是因為一些自由機對身體的傷害
cell aging etc.
細胞的老化 等等
Some DNA damage will lead to this aging path
DNA的一些損傷 就會走向這個老化的路
But this aging process if you have some
但是這個老化的過程 如果你有搭配一些
the disease i just mentioned
我剛剛提到的疾病的話
it's going to be faster
它的速度是會更快的
What about the state of aging?
那麼老化的狀態呢 就是
uh when it happens
呃 發生的時候
Our bodies may be in a long-term
我們身體可能會處於一種長期的
a low-grade inflammatory state
低度的一個發炎的狀態
With some endocrine wet strips and metabolic changes
搭配一些內分泌的濕條跟代謝的改變
uh lead to
呃 引而為現
But gradually, some phenomena will occur
但逐漸的呢 就會有一些現象的發生
I just talked about frailty
我剛剛講到衰弱症
But before this debility
但是 這個衰弱症之前
Maybe something like these
可能就譬如說有這些
In fact, there are also some mental symptoms
其實由這兒也搭配一些精神的症狀
easy to say
譬如說容易
melancholy forget
憂鬱啦 沾忘
Some anemia, lack of strength
有一些貧血 沒有力氣
The problem with swallowing flames
搭配吞焰的問題
wet urine
遍蜜尿濕淨
or insomnia, malnutrition
或者是失眠 營養不良
Sarcopenia
肌少症
often as i just said
常常就我剛剛講到的
because of disease
因為跟疾病有關
such a person in such a state
這樣的一個有這樣狀態人
often used a lot of drugs
常常也是用了很多很多藥物
people who take a lot of drugs
吃了很多藥的人
What about these risk factors?
那這些危險因子呢
Later it will show a
後來就會表現出一個
debilitating condition
衰弱的狀況
is that there will be several aspects
就是會有幾個面向
like sudden weight loss
像體重突然的減輕
So we observed an old man
所以我們觀察到一個老人
Suddenly we said that it is not good to be too fat
突然我們說人太胖不好
But if you are already fat
但是如果是已經胖的體質
If you observe a fat old man
你如果觀察到一個胖胖的老人
suddenly lost weight
突然瘦了
that's not a good
這就不是一個好
if he is not there
他如果沒有在
It seems to be eating healthy
好像就是健康吃
or love sports
或者是情運動
Sudden weight loss is a warning sign
突然的瘦就是一個警訊
It's a warning sign of weakness
就是衰弱的警訊
sudden weight loss
體重突然的減輕
Then he often feels exhausted
然後他常常覺得筋疲力盡
His hand grip is not strong enough
他手的握力很不夠
I have no strength to hold things
拿東西 沒有力氣
It's natural that I don't want to go out.
這個自然而然的就不想出去動了
I used to take a walk, but now I don't take a walk anymore.
本來散步的 現在也不散步了
I don't do some things normally
平常做一些事都不做了
Walking, the speed is getting slower and slower
走路呢 速度越來越慢
These phenomena are the so-called swerving
這幾個現象就是所謂的swerving
when this happens right after
這個正後發生的時候
susceptible to injury and infection
就會容易受傷 容易感染
easy to fall
容易跌倒
that leads to disability and death
那導致失能依賴跟死亡
So basically it's an old you health issue
所以基本上這個就是一個老您健康的問題
so i'm talking about
所以我現在談的是
It's really full of problems behind
真的是滿後面的問題
But I think people in their fifties and sixties
但是我想五六十歲的人
should start to understand the problem
應該要開始了解這個問題
Even people in their thirties and forties
甚至三四十歲的人
you can also follow
你也可以關注
You can also help the elderly in your own home
也可以幫助自己家的裡面的老人
So the phenomenon just now
所以剛剛那個現象
In fact, it is what I just called the elderly positive group
其實就是我剛剛所謂的老年正後群
Here's what I just said
這邊就是我剛剛講的一些情況
It broadly refers to health problems that are common among the elderly
它泛指的是老年族群常見的健康問題
The problem with these forces
這些勢力的問題
Weakness Forgetfulness Depression Malnutrition
衰弱 沾忘 憂鬱 營養不良
cognitive function problems
認知功能問題
urinary incontinence etc incontinence
尿失禁等等失禁
And even some pain in the window
還有甚至一些入窗疼痛
these are included
這些都是包含在內的
But we just talked about these phenomena
可是我們剛剛講到這些現象
It means that of course there are some
它就是說當然有一些
Not necessarily only for the elderly
不見得是老年族群才有的
So do this for the elderly
所以針對老年族群來做這個
When discussing geriatric syndrome
老年症候群的探討的時候
We will focus more on frailty
我們比較會著重在衰弱症
Sarcopenia and falls
肌少症跟跌倒
This is the three persons who are the three sides of the same one
這個是三位是同樣一體的三面
Dementia is a little different
另外失智有一點點不一樣
just a little bit different
就是稍微有點不一樣
This is a system of muscles and balance
這個是肌肉以及平衡的一個系統
This dementia is a direction of our brain brand
這個失智是我們腦筋 brand 的一個方向
geriatric syndrome
那這些老年症候群
We found a strong correlation with nutritional status privacy patterns
我們發現跟營養狀況隱私形態非常有關
So what I'm going to talk about today is
所以我今天等一下講的就是
Some of our international literature
我們在一些國際上的文獻
Some information we have seen and our Taiwan
我們所看到的一些資料以及我們台灣
Especially the research done by our sustainable project
特別是我們永續計畫所做出來的研究
first let me tell you
首先我來跟大家講一下
Papers we have published in 2017
我們曾經發表的2017年發表的論文
We use Taiwan's Nutritional Health Survey
我們用台灣的營養健康狀況調查
Found that we Taiwan's elderly over 65 years old
發現到我們台灣65歲以上的老人
The so-called robust in the middle is completely fine
中間所謂robust就是完全沒問題的
40% without any signs of weakness
沒有任何衰弱現象的是40%
7.8% over the age of 65 are already frail
65歲以上有7.8%已經是在衰弱
What is weakness?
什麼叫做衰弱呢
The five aspects I just talked about
我剛剛講的那五個面向
If there are three such phenomena in the middle
中間如果有三個這樣的一個現象
so-called weakness
就是所謂的衰弱
What is it?
就是什麼手臥力過弱
walking too slowly
步行速度過慢
weight loss
體重下降
always feel tired
總是感覺疲憊
reduced physical activity
身體的活動就降低了
I don't have the strength and don't want to go out to do it
沒有力氣也不想出去做
three is called weakness
有三個就叫做衰弱
then one or two words
那麼一到兩個的話
pre-frailty
是所謂衰弱前期
In fact, people over the age of 65
其實65歲以上的老人
we look like this
我們這樣看起來就是
Sixty percent already have
六成都已經有
A phenomenon of more than one weakening
一個以上的一個衰弱的一個現象
Then I will
那下面我就
OK, what if I get here?
OK 我到這邊的話呢
I'm just telling you
我就是跟大家講一下
It's one of my main axes today
就是我今天的一個主軸
geriatric syndrome
就是老年症候群
Then I will talk about the following
那下面的話我就來講一下
as the body ages
就是隨著老化身體
What kind of situation is the change with the body
與身體的改變是什麼樣一個狀況
Then this might get some younger people thinking
那這個就可能讓一些更年輕的人去思想
I will
我以後
That is to say, how do we develop as human beings?
就是說我們人是怎麼樣發展
It will develop into the weakened state I just mentioned
會發展到剛剛我講的那個衰弱的一個狀況
let's take a look
我們來看一下
the body mass index
這個身體質量指數
Both waist circumference and waist circumference are well-known indicators of obesity
跟腰圍都是大家非常知道的一個肥胖指標
That obesity indicator
那這個肥胖指標
On the left is body mass index
左邊就是身體質量指數
We all know the weight
大家知道是體重
In addition to height
除上身高
divide twice
除兩次
Or divide by the square of the height
或者除上身高的平方
In our impression
我們的印象中
That is, whether people have followed from the student days
就是人是不是隨著從學生時代以後
just getting fatter
就是越來越胖
Is it in our impression?
我們的印象中是這樣吧
Look at the books in the nutrition and health survey
你看看這個是營養健康調查裡面的書籍
We see ages from 19 to 44 to middle age 45 to 64
我們看到從19到44歲到中年45到64歲
Inside this frame are the elderly
這個框框裡面就是老年人
He sure is only going to get better and better
他確實身體質量只會越來越高
But after entering the age of 65
但是當進入65歲老年之後
In men, he actually falls down
在男性其實他是往下掉的
After the age of 65, the weight will come down
到65歲以後體重性就下來了
Many people may be very happy when this comes down
這個下來的時候可能很多人很開心
but it's not
可是其實並不是
shouldn't be too happy
並不應該太開心
you should pay attention
你應該要注意
because it might be a
因為這可能就是一個
the mass of your body
你的身體的質量
some parts have been reduced
就有一些部分就已經減少了
that's what it means
是這個意思
the same waist
那同樣的腰圍也是
You see the waist was thinner when you were young
你看年輕的時候腰比較細
getting thicker
越來越粗
At the age of 65 to 69
到了65歲到69歲這個時候
still in the upper body
還在上身當中
But after the age of 70, it will come down
但一過了70歲以後就下來了
The man saw a phenomenon
那男性有看到一個現象
Then women are different
那麼女性比較不一樣
women age
女性就是隨著年齡
So the old lady is very obedient when she arrives.
所以老太太到了後來都是很服態的
This is a phenomenon in Taiwan
這是我們台灣的一個現象
But will women go through this process later?
可是女性是不是後來會走這個過程是會的
because we investigate
因為我們一樣調查
when doing this national
做這個全民的時候
but the very old are less
但非常老的人數就比較少
So there is no way to watch it after this 80
所以沒有辦法去在這個80歲以後再看
In fact, when women are old
其實女性到後來年老的時候
Maybe after 90s
可能90幾歲以後
They are also weight will BMI physical acceleration
他們也是體重會BMI身體加速
will come down
是會下來
So a drop like this is a sign of aging
所以這樣的一個下來就是一個老化的一個徵兆
It's a sign of geriatric syndrome
就是進入老年症候群的一個徵兆
Women are on this picture also see the upper
女性是在這個圖上還看到上層
Because our last grouping is 80 years old
因為我們最後一個分組是80歲
It also showed a rapid loss of body mass in women
這也顯示出女性的身體質量的快速減少
is later than men
是比男性要來得晚
Men are earlier
男性是比較早的
There is such a phenomenon
有這樣的一個現象
So let's look at body mass index
那我們來看一下身體質量指數
with our bones in the middle
中間有我們的骨骼
have our muscles
有我們的肌肉
and our fat all put together
還有我們的脂肪都放在一起
It is not easy to make an understanding
不容易來做一個了解
What about our muscles?
那我們的肌肉是怎麼樣呢
That is, the blue above is male
就是上面藍色是男性
the following is female
下面是女性
If our men are young people from 19 to 44 years old
我們男性如果從19歲到44歲的年輕族群
What about over 80 years old?
比到80歲以上的話呢
Muscle is 6 kg less
肌肉是少了6公斤
The current situation of Taiwanese
現在台灣人的情況
Then the female is less than 2.2 kg
那麼女性少的是2.2公斤
that debilitating condition
那衰弱的狀況
Appearing here is the weakness I just mentioned.
這邊顯現就是我剛剛講的衰弱
Early asthenia and no signs of asthenia
衰弱前期跟沒有任何衰弱現象
you can see weak people
你可以看到衰弱的人
How about compared to people who are not weak?
跟沒有衰弱的人比起來的話呢
It's 6kg short
就是差了6公斤
There are old people here
那這邊都是老人
because in young people
因為在年輕人
We didn't do his debilitating assessment
我們沒有去做他的衰弱評估
such a young woman
那麼年輕的女性
For older women, the difference is 1.5 kg
老年女性的話是差1.5公斤
but i want to emphasize
但是我要強調
just let everybody see us from this young adult
就讓大家看到我們從這個年輕成人
to old age
到老年
You see our muscular men lose 6kg
你看我們的肌肉男性少6公斤
Women lost 2.2 kg
女性少了2.2公斤
Of course women and men at the beginning
當然女性跟男性在開始的時候
It's about 20kg short
就差了大概快20公斤
men and women have big muscles
男女的肌肉有很大
So women often have muscle soreness, these things
所以就是女性常常有肌肉 痠痛啊 這些事情
because women have less muscle, that's one reason
是因為女性的肌肉比較少 這是一個原因
The other thing is hemoglobin, which is an indicator of normal blood.
那另外一件事情就是血紅素 血紅素這是一個平血的指標
We can see males as young adults versus this middle aged
我們可以看到男性在年輕成人跟這個中老年的時候
His hemoglobin is very high, maintaining around 15
他這個血紅素都非常的高 維持在15左右
But as soon as he enters old age he declines
但是一進入老年之後他就下降
Therefore, it is very difficult for men to level blood. Men only have two points to level blood.
所以男性非常不容易平血的 男性只有兩個點會平血
One is around the age of 12 when he grows very fast he will flat blood
一個就是在12歲左右 他長得非常快的時候他會平血
Then when they grow into adults, men will no longer have flat blood
然後一長成人之後男性就不再會平血了
It wasn't until he was old that he started to have flat blood.
一直到他老的時候才會開始有平血的現象
Well women are not, women are a problem at a young age because of the need to reproduce
那麼女性不是 女性是在年輕的時候因為需要生育的一個問題
Therefore, when women are young, their hemoglobin is only a little over 12
所以女性年輕的時候的血紅素就只有12多一點
After menopause, women's hemoglobin will rise
那麼女性停經之後 血紅素會上升
I no longer feel dizzy and lack of energy.
就不再頭昏腦臟沒有精神了
But after the sixties
可是呢到了六十幾歲以後
will also slowly decline a little bit
也會緩緩的下降一點點
This range is very small
這個幅度是很小
But it is a significant drop
但是是滿顯著的一個下降
So what does this tell us about the problem?
那麼這個告訴我們什麼問題呢
It's about energy
就是有關於精力的問題
means no strength or anything
就是說沒有力氣或什麼
This is related to the aspect of anemia
這跟貧血這個面向
also have some relationship
也是有一些關係的
So there's this one
所以到了還有這樣的一個
A phenomenon we should pay attention to
一個現象我們要注意
The other one is lung function
那另外一個就是肺功能
inhalation of this oxygen
這個氧氣的吸入
Inhalation is the same as we often use
吸入這件事跟我們常常會用
The so-called maximal forced expiratory volume
這個所謂的最大用力呼氣量
forced expiratory volume in the first second
跟第一秒用力呼氣量
Then this is related to a
那這個相關的是一個
spirometry problems
肺活量的問題
then this is a
那麼這個是一個
This is the so-called trachea
這個就是所謂氣管
A question on Tongtong
通通上的一個問題
you can see that is to say
你可以看到就是說
in young adults
在年輕成人
He has a lung capacity of four liters
他肺活量有四公升
In the eighties, there are two liters left
到了八十幾歲剩下兩公升
dropped by half
就下降了一半
This is also quite influential
這個也是相當有影響力的
Women drop from 3 liters to 1.5 liters
女性從三公升降到一點五公升
Then this forced expiratory volume in the first second
那麼這個第一秒用力呼氣量
also dropped a lot
也是下降非常多
If some prospective data
如果用一些前瞻性的數據
you can see that is to say
你可以看到就是說
This waste activity volume and this exhalation volume in the first second
這個廢活量以及第一秒的這個呼出量
When the degree of a person's weakness
跟一個人的衰弱的程度的時候
are very relevant
都是非常相關的
It is also related to the amount of a person's muscles.
跟一個人的肌肉的量也都是相關的
Of course, this causal relationship is difficult to say
當然這個因果關係很難講
Is it because your muscles are lacking
是不是因為你的肌肉缺乏了
so your breath
所以你的呼吸
You can't have such a large amount of waste
你沒有辦法再有這麼樣大的這個廢活量
It should be said that it may be the cause of the muscles
應該說起來可能是肌肉的原因
muscular cause
肌肉的原因
so this
所以這個
one theory is this
一論就是這個
exercise your muscles
你這個肌肉的鍛鍊
Also includes this waste activity
還包含了這個廢活量
Because the muscles of the whole body and the transverse lattice
因為全身的肌肉跟橫格肌
These muscles are all related
這些肌肉都是相關的
This is also weak
這一點也是跟衰弱的
is very closely related
是非常息息相關的
In addition, it is often used to measure
那麼另外常常用來測量的
It is the five aspects I just mentioned
就是我剛剛講到的那個五個面向
It's Linda Freed's five facets
是Linda Freed的他的五個面向
One is walking speed and the other is lying force
一個就是步行速度一個是臥力
You can see this green is male
你可以看到這個綠色是男性
gray is female descended
灰色是女性下降了
This is because we only test the elderly
這個是因為我們這個只有測老人
So from the age of 65 to the age of 80, it has dropped by 1.4
所以從65歲到80幾歲來看是下降了1.4
down by 1.3
下降了1.3
What about this power?
這個臥力的話呢
This place is in kilograms
這個地方是用公斤數
Lost 8.6kg from 60s to 80s
從60幾歲到80幾歲下降了8.6公斤
Female dropped 4.2kg
女性下降了4.2公斤
So we look at a drop like this
所以我們看這樣的一個下降
so these are
所以這一些都是
The parameters I just talked about
我剛剛講的那些參數
Everyone can pay attention
都是大家可以留意的
just like i used to
就是像我過去
because I do nutritional surveys
因為我做營養調查
Once I asked someone from my team to help me
有一次我就請我的團隊的人幫我
i think i'm in good health
我覺得我身體很健康
Measured my waste activity
測了一下我的廢活量
They said teacher, your amount of wasted work is below average
他們就說老師你的廢活量是在平均之下
i was startled
我就嚇了一跳
I said it turned out that my waste activity
我說原來我的廢活量
That part of me might need some work out too
我這個部分可能也需要鍛鍊
Then there is also the reclining force that can be measured.
那還有臥力也可以測
Hemoglobin can also be measured
血紅素也可以測
These are now with some tapering
這些都是在現在有一些漸減
start gradually incorporating these items
開始逐漸納入這些項目
so everyone can understand
所以大家可以來理解
A health condition of my own
自己這一塊的一個健康狀況
The development of this course of fear is generally considered to be
衰畏的這個病程發展一般是認為了
related to genetic and environmental factors
跟遺傳因素環境因素都有關係的
The other common interaction of these factors
那這些因素的其他共同的這個交互作用
damage some cells in our body
會造成我們身體的一些細胞的損傷
or a lesion at some molecular level
或者一些分子層次的一個損傷
This damage will affect some functional decline of multiple system organs
這損傷就會影響到多重的系統器官的一些功能下降
Including brain, endocrine, immune, muscle, heart, blood vessel, breathing, kidney, etc.
包含腦、內分泌、免疫、肌肉、心臟、血管、呼吸、腎臟等等
I just mentioned things like breathing, muscles
我剛才有提到像呼吸、肌肉這些
after this drop
在這個下降之後呢
Without proper nutrition such a lifestyle
如果沒有妥當的這樣的一個生活形態好的營養
and use proper physical activity to maintain your body's muscles
以及用適當的體能活動來保持自己的身體的肌肉
and cell function
和細胞的功能的話
It is easy to develop symptoms of dread
就很容易發展到衰畏的症狀
This is what I just mentioned when something unexpected happens
這個就是我剛剛提到當意外事件發生的時候就
metabolic syndrome
產生了代謝症候群
Next, I will use this picture again.
那下面呢 我再用這個圖呢
let me tell you about this
來跟大家講一下這個
The vicious cycle of aging and disease
老化與疾病的這個惡性循環的
a state
一個狀態
so everyone can understand
所以大家可以理解
Sometimes we also observe
有的時候我們也觀察到
some changes in your body
自己身體的一些改變
you may know
你可能就會知道
We are all aging
我們人都在不斷的老化當中
and there may be some diseases
而且可能會有些疾病
sorry this is in english
很抱歉 這是用英文的
This is really hard to change to Chinese
這張實在難以改為中文
So I will speak clearly when I speak
所以我就用講的時候講清楚一點
So in the process
所以在這個過程中
Did we just talk about it
我們剛剛講到是不是
our muscles will decrease
我們的肌肉會減少
What about when we lose muscle?
當我們肌肉減少的時候呢
It will happen that a phenomenon is
它會發生一個現象就是
My so-called basal metabolic rate drops
我的所謂的基礎代謝率就會下降
Because muscles are very energy-consuming
因為肌肉是非常耗能的
when you lose muscle now
當你現在肌肉減少了
you don't need so much energy
你就不需要這麼多能量
your metabolic rate drops
你的代謝率就會下降
What about after a drop?
一下降了之後呢
your need your this
你的需要 你的這個
You need to burn fewer calories
你需要就是用掉的熱量也減少
It means you are a person with less muscle
就是說你一個比較少肌肉的人
You just sleep over there and you drain energy
你就在那邊睡覺 你消耗力
So in this case the words
所以在這種情況下的話
your appetite may be affected
你就可能就食慾就會受到影響
You don't need so many calories
你不需要這麼多熱量了
your appetite is affected
你食慾受到影響
Did you start not wanting to eat?
你是不是就開始不想吃飯了
you don't want to eat after
你不想吃飯之後
Just slowly this nutrient
就慢慢的這個營養素
less will come in
進來的就會少
The cycle will continue after less
少了之後這個循環就會繼續
the so-called negative calorie balance
就是所謂的熱量的負平衡
After negative caloric balance
熱量負平衡之後
after your calorie loss
你熱量少了之後
do you have less muscle
你是不是肌肉就更少
you enter a vicious cycle
你就進入一個惡性的循環
The part that can't move
那走不動的那一塊
is to say
是在於說
when you have less muscle
當你肌肉少的時候
you have no strength
你就沒有什麼力氣
Then your VO2
然後你的這個VO2
is your oxygen
就是你的氧氣
VO2 will drop
VO2就會下降
The amount of oxygen you can breathe in drops
你能吸進來的氧氣就下降
like this case
那像這個情況下
you walk slower
你走路速度就會慢
when you walk slowly
你走路速度慢的時候
your activity
你的活動
you don't want to go out
你就不想出去動了
So you're less active again
所以你的活動量又減少
Then further reduce
那就更進一步的減少
caloric needs
熱量的需求
eat less calories
熱量就又吃得更少
what about less
更少之後怎麼樣呢
Nutrients come in less
營養素進來就更少
After that, you will have less energy
那少了之後你就更沒力氣
so it's a vicious cycle
所以這是一個惡性循環
So when we understand such a situation
所以當我們了解這樣一個狀況的時候
If you find out that it is the old man in the family
如果你發現就是家裡的老人
when there is such a situation
有這樣的一個情況的時候
you have to break it
你也要把它打斷
Your cycle can be interrupted
你這個這個cycle是可以把它打斷的
you just have to give it some broken links
你就是要給它做一些斷鏈
Start with the simpler of course
從當然是比較簡單的開始
So exercise and diet are closely related
所以運動跟飲食是息息相關
Although I am talking about diet today
我今天雖然講的是飲食
But exercise is essential
但是運動這塊不可少
But because there are more sports information
但是因為運動的資訊比較多
Everyone knows how to exercise
大家比較懂得怎麼樣去做運動
So today I just focus on
所以我今天是就是專注在
I am more professional this is
我自己比較專業的這個就是
part of nutrition
營養的一個部分
So what I'm going to say is
所以我要講的就是說
This vicious cycle can be broken
這個惡性循環是可以被打破的
that may have to wait until the end to ask the question
那可能要等最後來問問題
we will continue
我們就繼續
So when I talk about this side now
所以我現在講到這邊的時候
I'll start talking to you
我就開始跟大家講一下
besides sports
除了運動
This exercise is definitely to do
這運動絕對是要做的
and in motion
而且有運動中
There are many tricks, there are many faces
有很多的竅門 有很多的面相
All kinds of different sports we don't mention today
各種不同的運動 在我們今天不提
Let's talk about it later
以後大家再來探討
Then I will start talking about it today. Good with exercise.
那我今天就開始講 好 搭配運動
then how do we eat
那我們要怎麼樣的吃
Only then can this phenomenon
才能夠就是讓這個現象
able to make a reply
能夠做一個回復
then let me tell you first
那我首先跟大家講一下
is of course we have to take a look
就是我們當然要看一下
current scientific literature
現在的科學的文獻
The current scientific literature is debilitated in this
現在的科學文獻在這個衰弱
What about the little part?
基少的這一塊呢
Basically most of them are talking
基本上大多數都是在講
protein
蛋白質
that's ok i can say that
那可以 我可以這樣講就是說
Whether transverse or forward
不論是橫斷綿圓或前瞻性
That is, you may not know the term
也就是大家可能不太清楚這個名詞
but it doesn't matter
但是沒有關係
or some interventional experimental research
或者是一些介入實驗性的研究
Both have supported protein and frailty
都已經支持蛋白質跟衰弱症
is negatively correlated
是有負相關
mean to say
意思就是說
you eat more protein
你的蛋白質吃得多
you won't be weak easily
你就不容易衰弱
you eat less protein
你的蛋白質吃得少
you are more likely to weaken
你就比較容易衰弱
This is especially about the elderly
這個特別是在講老人這一塊
so older people
所以年紀大的人
That is to say, this protein cannot be ignored
就是说这个蛋白质是不可轻忽的
I remember two days ago I was with a colleague
我记得前两天我还跟我一个同事
so-called advanced intellectuals
就是所谓高级知识分子
We all happened to be vegetarians.
我们正好大家都是去吃了素
Be vegetarian because when we eat out
吃素 因为我们在外食的时候
I think vegetarian bento is safer
觉得素便当做得比较保险一点
Because its oil will not be a bad oil
因为它那个油不会是不好的油
But this vegetarian bento happens to be inside
但是这个素便当正好里面
It's all vegetables without any protein
全都是菜 没有任何的蛋白质
so i told the restaurant
所以我就跟那个餐厅说
can we have some protein
可不可以给我们来一点蛋白质
Then my colleague said
那我的同事他就讲说
no no no no protein
不要了 不要了 不要蛋白质
I said why
我说为什么
He said the burden of winning is too heavy
他说胜账负担太重
Then I tell him it's important
那我就跟他讲很重要
He said it was especially important for the elderly
他就说尤其对老人重要
Then my colleague immediately told me that
那我的同事就立刻告诉我说
I think old people just shouldn't eat too much protein
我认为老人就是不该吃太多的蛋白质
The burden of victory is too heavy
胜账负担太重
Then of course I'm not good
那当然我也就不好
but i know
但是我就知道
This means that many people have such a concept
这表示说很多人都有这样的一个概念
That is to say, the elderly should not eat too much protein
就是说老人不该吃太多的蛋白质
May be physically taxing
可能会对身体有负担
Then I want to tell you that
那我要跟大家讲就是说
The current scientific literature is
现在的科学文献是
Supports the release of protein and herbal medicines Interrelated
支持蛋白質和燒藥證釋 互相相關的
Then these studies
那麼這些研究的話
I have no way to talk to you today
我今天也沒有辦法跟大家多講
It's probably an egg balancing study
它多半是用一種蛋平衡研究
that is, discussing a person
就是說探討一個人
how much protein do i give it
我給它多少的蛋白質
and see how much it excretes
然後看它排泄多少
Which point will reach the balance
再哪一個點會達到平衡
Most of these studies
多半是這樣的研究
Of course there are new ways
當然現在還有新的方法
use this stable
用穩定的這個
Isotopes of ISO TOG
ISO TOG的同位素
Add a label to that amino acid and eat it
把那個胺基酸加上一個標的之後吃下去
Then look in the middle of the exhaled air
然後看呼出的氣體中間
how much of this
有多少這個
These isotopes use this method
這些同位素用這種方法
many ways to make
很多的方法做出來
Well, we don't have such research in Taiwan at all.
那我們台灣完全沒有這樣的研究
So in order to understand Taiwanese
所以我們為了要了解台灣人
How much protein should I eat?
到底要吃多少蛋白質呢
We used another method
我們用了另外一個方法
This method is to say
這個方法就是說
AI for Nutrients
了解營養素的AI
AI is the so-called appropriate intake
AI就是所謂的適當攝取量
this is a method
這是一個方法
This method is acceptable in nutrition
這個方法是在營養學裡是可接受的
it means
它意思就是說
If you do not have the appropriate data
你如果沒有適當的數據的時候
you just evaluate that
你就是去評估那個
How much do those people who have no problem at all eat?
那些完全沒有問題人他到底吃多少
Because we do not have such research in Taiwan
因為我們台灣並沒有這樣的研究
Then these researches are being done by several groups around the world
那這些研究在全球也就是有幾個group在做
The egg balance study I just talked about
我剛剛講的蛋平衡研究
So we use Taiwan from 2014 to 2017
那所以我們就用台灣2014年到2017年
This nutritional data in 2017
2017年的這個營養大化資料
let's do the math
我們來做一下計算
We just divide the elderly into
我們就是把老年人把它分成
Frailty Non-frailty Early stage of frailty and frailty
衰 非衰弱 衰弱的前期跟衰弱
Let's see, everyone just look at the data on the right.
來看 大家就看這個右邊的數據就好了
Here is the number of people doing statistics
那這邊是做統計的人數
Then the most important thing for us to see is that there is no problem.
那我們最要看的就是說沒有問題
These elderly people without debilitating diseases
沒有衰弱症的這些老人
what is his protein intake
他的蛋白質攝取量是多少呢
We see that it is 1.2 grams per kilogram of body weight
我們看到是每公斤體重1.2克
1.21 male female is 1.22
1.21男性女性是1.22
this is a median
這是一個中位數
Of course, this is a concept of our statistics
當然這是我們統計學的一個概念
That means I don't use averages
就是說我不會用平均值
instead of the median
不用的是中位數
what does the median mean
中位數是什麼意思呢
is the most people
就是最多的人
The most lack of people here
這裡面的人最缺
These people in the middle are all ingesting this amount
居中的這些人都是攝取這樣的量
Then we dare not use the average
那我們也不敢用平均值
Why? Because people eat protein and some people eat a lot
為什麼?因為人吃蛋白質有些人會吃很多
Incredibly many
多的不得了
So once you average down, the average value will be skewed.
所以你一平均下去把平均值拉歪掉了
So we use the median
所以我們就用中位數
We can see debilitated people who weigh a kilogram a day
我們可以看到衰弱的人是一天一公斤體重
eat less than a gram
吃不到一克
Pre-failure is centered
衰弱前期是居中
Then this number may not mean anything to you
那這個數目可能對大家沒有什麼
Maybe you see this number and think its nothing
可能你看到這數也覺得沒什麼
but i want to tell you
但是我要跟大家講
Globally International Recommendations for Protein
就在全球的國際的對於蛋白質建議
almost all have a number
幾乎都有一個數目
That number is 1.2
那個數目就是1.2
Doesn't matter if it's Canadian or EU people
就不管是加拿大的歐盟的人
he basically said
他基本上就說
An old man needs to eat 1.2 grams per kilogram of body weight a day
一個老人一天他每公斤體重要吃1.2克
Then this 1.2 grams is meaningless to everyone
那這個1.2克對大家來說也沒什麼意思
I don't know how much 1.2 grams is
我也不知道1.2克是多少
I'll talk to you later
我等一下要跟你們講
you can eat like this
你怎樣吃就可以吃到這個樣子
So this 1.2 grams is a magic trick
所以這1.2克是一個魔術
Same as Magic Number
Magic Number一樣
But now there are actually some other children
可是現在還其實還有一些其他的子男
yes
是
Most people are like this, but if you are in a
一般人是這樣 但是如果你是處於一種
For example, the state of illness, the state of lying down for a long time
譬如說生病的狀態 長期臥常的狀態
In fact, your body's response to protein
你其實你身體對於蛋白質的這個
Utilization is poor and you have to add more
利用率很差 你還要再增加
Can be increased to 1.4
可以增加到1.4
Even some people 1.6 can have such a guide
甚至有的人1.6都可以有這樣的一個指南
But one thing I'm happy to say is that
但是我很高興來說的一個事就是
We use this AI's orphan algorithm
我們用這種AI的孤算法
The figures obtained in Taiwan are similar to those obtained internationally.
在我們台灣所得到的數字 跟國際上是可以接軌的 是類似的
Then this data we also
那這個數據我們也
It is recommended to go to the National Health Service of our country
建議到我們國家的那個國民健康署
what does that mean
那這到底是什麼意思呢
Then I will now test because of such a data
那我現在就因為這樣的一個數據 我們也來檢驗
Taiwan
台灣
We all know the advice to the people
對於民眾所做的建議 大家都知道
Our government promulgated a policy called the American-Japanese Dietary Guidelines
我們政府頒布一個叫美日飲食指南
This American-Japanese Dietary Guide is precisely calculated
這個美日飲食指南它是經過精密的計算
That is, if you keep eating
就是你如果照著吃的話
All your nutrients will be up to standard
你的各種營養素都是會達標的
But back then
可是當年
when doing this
在做這個東西的時候呢
No one knows that the body weight of the old man's body is 1.2 grams
沒有人知道老人美工精體重量是1.2克
At that time, we used the target of 1.0 instead of 1.2
當時我們用的標的是1.0 不是用1.2
So now I want to say okay let's check it out
所以現在我就想說好吧 那我們來檢驗看看
Will everyone be getting enough of what the country recommends?
按照國家的建議 大家會不會吃夠呢
So in fact, there are some recommended calories for each age group
所以其實每一個年齡層都有一些建議熱量
Make some suggestions according to the weight and height of our Taiwanese, you see
按照我們台灣人的體重身高來做一些建議 你看
So in fact, the recommendations are very detailed for people aged 19 to 34
所以其實建議的非常細 19到34歲的人
If he eats such 1850 calories
如果他吃到這樣1850大卡
Or he eats 2150 to above
或他吃到2150到以上
Is his protein enough enough to reach 1 kg 1.2 grams
他的蛋白質夠不夠 夠的 達到1公斤 1.2克
Really boys are enough, 31 to 50 years old
真的男生都夠的 31到50歲
It's all OK because even a 71-year-old
都OK 因為即便到71歲的老人
If he eats 1650 calories he will be enough
如果他吃1650大卡他也夠
But we found that if it is on the female side
可是我們發現就是說如果在女性這一邊的話呢
From young women he has some people who eat very little
從年輕女性他就有一些人吃很少
1450 calories only
1450大卡而已
In old age, some women in their 70s only eat 1300 calories
到了老年 70幾歲有些女性只吃到1300大卡
Everyone knows that many weight loss diets are 1200 calories
大家知道很多減肥飲食是1200大卡
So Yiqiansans understanding of non-film and television is not far behind
所以一千三理解非影视也差不了多远
So for those who are older and eat less
所以对于这些年纪大又吃得少的人
His protein is not enough
他的蛋白质是不够的
So here's a thing
所以这边讲了一个事情
In fact, there is usually a general rule
其实一边平常都是有一个通则
That is if you eat very little people
就是说如果你吃很少的人
you are prone to malnutrition
你很容易营养不良
So because in the past everyone was
那所以因为过去大家都在
Have you ever thought about being fat?
一直想着肥胖这种问题嘛
I think it's better to eat less
都觉得吃少一点好
But the fact here is that if you eat very little
但是这里事实就是说如果你吃得很少
In old age you are very prone to malnutrition
到了老年你非常容易营养不良
If there is not enough protein, it will enter the stage of weakness
蛋白质会不够就会进入衰弱这个阶段
So let me mention this to you first.
所以这个我在这边先跟大家提一下
So now we are talking to the government
所以我们现在有跟政府讲说
Your dietary advice for people who eat less
你对于吃得比较少的人的这个饮食建议
to modify
要做修改
Otherwise these people may fall into protein deficiency
不然的话这些人可能会落入蛋白质不足
Especially the camp French
就是特别是营法族这一块
Then I will tell you more clearly later.
那我等一下还会再跟大家讲来更清楚
Because of this throughout my speech today
因为我今天的这个在整个演讲
I just want to say that you don't just listen to some principles
我就希望说大家不光是听一些原则
You really can make a diagnosis of your own diet
你真正的就是可以替你自己的飲食做一個診斷
so i'll make it clearer later
所以我等一下會講得更清楚
OK so now I'm done with protein
OK 所以現在蛋白質我講完了
That is to say, protein is the most concerned in the world
就是說國際上最關注的就是蛋白質
to address the weakness
來針對衰弱這一點
Then our Taiwan data
那我們台灣的數據
It seems to be consistent with the international data
似乎也跟國際的數據是吻合的
Then in addition
那麼另外就是說
Frailty is not only related to protein
衰弱症除了和蛋白質有關
Is it not related to other nutrients?
難道和其他的營養素沒有關係嗎
We found in the literature
我們發現在文獻上
I saw that it is related to many trace elements
就看到說他跟很多的微量元素都是相關的
And it seems that there is a phenomenon that
而且好像有個現象就是
Nutrient deficient items
營養素缺乏的項目
more words
越多的話
the greater the chance that the person is debilitated
這個人是罹患衰弱症的這個機會就越大
that phenomenon
那這個現象
Actually it's a bit paradoxical
其實有一點吊詭
That is, I see that in the literature, apart from protein
就是我們我看到文獻中除了蛋白質以外
The lack of number one
文獻數第一的缺乏
Lack of document number B12 Lack of C
文獻數B12的缺乏C的缺乏
new lack
新的缺乏
have some correlation
都有一些相關性
But this correlation
但這個相關性
what does he mean
來講他到底是什麼意思
that's hard
那很難
We found information in our Taiwan Nutrition and Health Survey
我們發現在我們台灣的營養健康調查的資料
We use something called the 24-hour recall method
我們是用一種叫做24小時回憶法
means meeting someone
就是說碰到一個人
I clearly asked him what he ate 24 hours yesterday
我很清楚地問了他他昨天24小時吃了什麼
Made after accurate quantification by various methods of food model
用食物模型各種方法都精確定量之後做出來的
I just found out that people with sarcopenia in Taiwan
就發現在台灣這些衰肉症的人呢
Low protein number B2B12C
蛋白質偏低文人數B2B12C
Calcium manicure
鈣質美甲
30,000 tails of polyvinyl alcohol are low in fatty acids
30千尾多元不保脂肪酸都偏低
When we see such a phenomenon
當我們看到這樣的一個現象的時候
Think from the standpoint of a nutritionist
以一個營養學家的立場來想
I'd think maybe that's not the case
我就會覺得可能不是這麼回事
It must be that he ate less.
應該是他什麼都吃少了
so you can see everything
所以什麼東西你都看得到
Because it is impossible to say that all of the
因為不可能說是全部都涉及
it's hard to say
這個就很難講了
So one conjecture might be that
所以一個推測可能就是說
Is it just eating too little?
是不是就是吃得太少了
will be such a phenomenon
會是這樣的現象
And if we know that these many nutrients
而且如果我們知道這些這麼多營養素
If I supplement all these nutrients with vitamins
如果我就把這些營養素都用維他命補了
can it be
難道就可以嗎
So we have to clarify
所以我們必須要去釐清
what kind of reason
到底是什麼樣的一個緣故
So we go one step further
所以我們又進一步的
let's discuss
來探討一下
It's the old man in Taiwan
就是台灣老人
If he is debilitated
他如果有衰弱症的話
his six categories of food
他的六大類食物
his overall diet
就是他整體的飲食型態
what is it like
到底是一個什麼樣子
then let me tell you
那我來跟大家說一下
This is male data
這個是男性的數據
I don't know if this will be a little difficult
不知道這個會不會有一點困難
but i said slowly
但是我慢慢的說
means you see this
就是說你看到這個
Men without debilitating disorders
沒有衰弱症人的男性
His average calorie intake is 2170 calories a day
他的平均熱量是一天2170大卡
But when it comes to debility
可是到衰弱症的時候
He is 1898 kcal
他是1898大卡
So about a 200 calorie difference
所以大約差了200大卡
He used to eat less overall
他之前就是整體來說吃得少了
In the early stage of frailty, I borrowed from the central
衰弱症前期就借在中央
that you different heat people
那你那不同的熱量的人
he is different
他就有不同的
In fact, the six categories of this proposal
其實六大類的這個建議
What are the six categories of recommendations?
什麼叫六大類建議呢
in fact
就是其實說
When we generally make dietary advice
我們一般在做飲食建議的時候
Divide food into six categories
會把食物分成六個大類
It means that you have to eat these six categories
意思就是說這六大類你都要吃
these foods
這些食物
And if you eat all of these six categories of food in the amount I suggest you
而你這六大類食物你都吃到我建議你的份量的話
You don't have to worry, you have enough nutrients
你就不必擔心了你什麼營養素都是夠的
The teacher usually recommends that
老師通常建議是這樣
What about when your calories are low?
那麼當你的熱量少的時候呢
Your six categories of advice are less
你的六大類建議就比較少
For example, in this place, what I express with a forest-colored frame is its suggestion
譬如說這個地方我用森色的框框表達的就是它的建議
In fact, all stocks here are our staple food.
那這邊事實上全股就是我們的主食類
That is to say, it is suggested that three bowls of rice may be enough
就是說建議可能三碗飯就夠了
But we noticed that these debilitated people eat a lot
但是我們注意到這些衰弱人他飯吃的多
He only needs three bowls
他只要是三碗就夠了
But he ate three and a half bowls a day
但是他吃了三碗半一天
He ate more than
他的飯吃的超過了
Then look at this, on the other hand, this normal person eats slightly less than what he should eat
那你看這個反之這個正常人他飯稍微的少於他該吃的份量
his less
他的少一點
But as you can see, this bean fish meat egg is the so-called protein
但是大家看到這個豆魚肉蛋就是所謂那個蛋白質類
All kinds of meat, eggs, seafood
各種肉啊蛋啊海鮮
The weak man also eats less
這個衰弱人也吃得少
he also eats less
他也吃得少
Normally, with this early stage of weakness, he simply exceeds the amount
而正常跟這個衰弱前期他根本就超過量
But are they too much protein?
但是是不是他們的蛋白質過多呢
Actually they don't have much protein
其實他們蛋白質沒有過多
Another important source is milk
還有一個重要的來源就是奶類
Then our people don't drink milk
那我們國人都不喝奶
So there's a lot of protein missing here.
所以這邊就缺了一堆的蛋白質
and calcium
還有鈣質
so we can see
所以我們可以看到
if you're the one who didn't fall
如果你是一個沒有摔到的人
Actually your protein is just right
其實你的蛋白質是剛剛好的
The amount you eat is to mix milk and this
就是吃的量就是把奶類和這個
Salmon are just right together
鮭在一起是剛剛好的
Of course because its protein comes from non-dairy products
當然因為它的蛋白質是從非奶類過來
Of course these people are
當然這些人都是
Almost all Taiwanese are calcium deficient
我們台灣人幾乎都缺鈣
So our bones are a big problem
所以我們骨子酥鬆是一大問題
For this male of these people
那這些人的這個男性來講
Then the fruit didn't meet the standard
然後水果都沒有達標
And there is not enough fat
還有就是油脂也不夠
because we young people
因為我們一般年輕人
It's all too much oil
都是油吃太多了
But these old people have not reached the level of fat
可是這些老人卻油脂都沒有達到
This grease Taiwan's grease
這個油脂台灣的油脂
The recommended amount is the so-called five servings
建議量所謂的五份
This is six servings
這個就是六份
is very little is six teaspoons
是非常少是六茶匙
very little
非常的少
But the reason none of them reach is because
但他們都沒有達到的原因是
Old people dare not eat too much oil
老人都不敢吃太油
So it doesn't have enough calories
所以它的熱量也不夠
so you can see
所以可以看到
a diet is
一個飲食就是
slightly too much rice
飯稍微太多一點
Not enough protein, not enough milk
蛋白質不夠,牛奶也不夠
For men, it seems that vegetables and fruits are not enough
男性的話,好像蔬菜水果也不夠
low fat
油脂都偏少
So it's a situation where all kinds of things are not enough
所以是一個各種東西都不太夠的一個情況下
Well, women have a similar trend
那麼女性有一個類似的趨勢
The female we see is that her heat is not that big of a difference
女性我們看到就是她的熱量並沒有那麼大的一個差異
It's weak, and it didn't say anything special
就是衰弱的,並沒有說特別吃的
She basically eats much less than men
她基本上都是比男人吃的少很多
But no, there's not much difference between the three
但是並沒有,這三個並沒有太大差異
But this frail female is also what she almost should be.
但是這個衰弱的女性也是她差不多應該是
Eat an 80% full meal, three bowls, that is, almost 2:4 bowls are enough
吃個八分滿的飯,三碗,就是差不多2點4碗就夠
But she ate nearly three bowls of rice
但是她吃快到三碗飯
She also has less protein
她的蛋白質也比較少
I don't drink this milk
這個奶類都不喝
Very little fruit and very little fat
水果很少,油脂也很少
But we can see that women eat more vegetables
不過我們可以看到女性的蔬菜是吃得比較多的
So it feels like protein is really a key
所以可以感覺到就是蛋白質確實是一個關鍵
So we see such a diet pattern
所以我們看到這樣的一個飲食形態
there is an understanding
就有一個了解
So one of the properties just mentioned
所以剛剛講到的一個特質
That is to say, it seems that it is the time when the French people start to grow old
就是說似乎到了引法族年紀開始大的時候
Dont still use the concept of serving food with vegetables
不要還是以菜來配飯的概念
Because especially Taiwanese food
因為尤其是台灣人吃的飯
It's still rice
到現在都還是白飯
Nutrients in it
它裡面各種營養素
are not so rich
都是沒有那麼豐富的
protein doesn't seem to be enough
蛋白質似乎是不夠
There is also too little fat
還有油脂也太少
too few calories
熱量太少
We know these characteristics
這幾個特色我們了解
Then we use another angle
再來就是我們用另外一個角度
to explore the so-called dietary pattern
來探討所謂的飲食形態
Just to see how rough these six categories are.
就是去看看這六大類是很粗啦
What kind of food is that person choosing?
那到底是選用什麼樣的食物的人
He's not weak
他比較不是衰弱的
So we're going to look at this issue
所以我們就要看這個議題
Of course, first of all, look at the international
當然首先也看看國際上
what kind of information
有什麼樣的一個資料
Everyone knows the famous Mediterranean diet, right?
大家都知道很有名的地中海飲食對不對
because he is so famous
因為他太有名了
so almost what disease
所以幾乎什麼病
Everyone take this Mediterranean diet
大家都拿來和這個地中海飲食
let's discuss
來探討一下
So even debility
所以連衰弱症也是有
These ten are now internationally
這十現在國際上
The most important thing to discuss about dietary patterns is
探討飲食形態最主要的就是
Mediterranean Diet Discoveries
地中海飲食發現
You eat more when you are middle-aged or when you are old
你中年的時候多吃或老年的時候
Long-term intake if it is in the form of Mediterranean diet
長期的攝取如果是地中海飲食這個形態
Less prone to frailty
比較不容易得到衰弱症
And vice versa, if it's a Western diet
那反之呢 如果是西方飲食形態
Just a lot of red meat burgers vegetarian
就是很多的紅肉 漢堡 素食
It is easier to suffer from debilitation
這樣就會比較容易有衰弱症
This is a study of Westerners
這是西方人的研究
But after all, there is no way we can combine the Mediterranean diet
但是畢竟我們沒有辦法把地中海飲食
Just apply it to Taiwan
就套用到台灣嘛
I can learn a little
可以學一點啦
But there is no way to be completely like this
但是沒有辦法完全的是這樣的一個樣子
There is very little research on that Chinese in frailty
那華人的研究在衰弱症非常少
In the past there was only one Hong Kong study
過去只有一個香港研究
When we published the 207 paper
在我們發表207的論文的時候
Only Hong Kong has one
只有香港有一篇
But his entire study failed to find a relevant dietary pattern
但是他整個研究沒有找到一個相關的飲食形態
That also has something to do with his analysis method.
那也跟他的分析方法是有關係的
So we use what we just said
所以我們就用了剛剛講到的
The data of Taiwan's nutrition and health survey
那個台灣的營養健康調查的資料
explore this our this
探討這個我們的這個
this debilitating diet
這個衰弱的這個飲食
We publish in American Geriatrics Society
我們發表在美國老年醫學會
Magazine, take a look
雜誌 大家看一下
Then what method do we use?
那我們是用一個什麼方法呢
We use a simple dimensional analysis called data mining
我們用一種叫做資料採礦的一個簡維分析法
The so-called simple-dimensional analysis method is
所謂的簡維分析法就是
Think about it, don't we eat a lot of food?
你試想我們人吃的食物是不是很多啊
you have dozens of kinds you have vegetables
你有幾十種 你有蔬菜
Various fruits and vegetables with drinks
各種蔬菜水果有飲料
With milk, with beans, with seafood
有奶類 有豆類 有海鮮
After lots and lots of food we all went to ask
很多很多的食物我們都去詢問之後
this dimension is too big
這個維度太大了
And people don't say how to eat
而且人吃東西並不是怎麼說
It doesn't mean how long you eat this thing
並不是說這個東西你吃多久
Rather it is the emergence of a form
而是它是一個形態的出現
For example, if I assume I eat a lot of red meat
譬如說我假設我吃很多紅肉的話
I don't have room in my stomach for that
我肚子就沒有空間吃那個
For example, tofu or fish and shrimp
譬如說豆腐或者是魚蝦
Then I may be a person who likes meat very much
然後我可能我是很喜歡吃肉的人
I'm sure I can't eat too many vegetables
我就一定我的蔬菜沒辦法吃太多
Because there's no more space in my stomach
因為肚子也沒那個空間了
So food is a way of appearance
所以食物是一種形態的方式出現
We made such an induction
我們就做了這樣的一個歸納法
Then found a diet pattern
然後發現有個飲食形態
What about this diet?
這個飲食形態呢
wait a minute it's in english
我等一下這是英文的
I'll use the next one to put it together
我再用下一張把它整合出來
This diet pattern shows that
這飲食形態顯示就是說
if you have a form
如果你有一個形態
that form is
那個形態是
Why can't you take them apart and put them together?
怎麼講不能拆散就搭配在一起
is what you eat
就是你吃
a lot of fruit
很多一點的水果
Eat more lotus seeds
吃多一點的荷果種子
I also like to drink more tea
也喜歡喝多一點的茶
eat more vegetables
也吃多一點的蔬菜
The rice you eat is also whole grains
你吃的飯也都是全股雜糧
Then you have more protein
然後你的蛋白質是比較多的
Excuses
藉口類
you drink more milk
你喝比較多一點牛奶
You also eat more fish
你也吃比較多一點魚
of course
那當然
we may have a hard time saying
我們可能很難說
which one is it
到底是其中哪一個
But it could also mean
但是也可能就是說
Each of these has half an eye and a little character
其中每一個都有半眼一點角色
So in summary
所以歸納來講的話
The green part means
這個綠色的部分就是說
if you can
你如果都能
eat more than enough
比較吃適量足夠的
plant food
植物性的食物
You see this food contains vegetables
你看這個食物包含了蔬菜
What about fruits and plants?
水果還有植物性的什麼食物呢
staple food is plant-based
主食是植物性的
yes
沒錯
Nutmeg Seed Oil
荷果種子油類
The lotus seed is that it is oily
這個荷果種子就是它是油類的
A sort of
一種
We divide the oil into cooking oil
我們把油分成炒菜用油
and lotus seeds that you can eat as a snack
以及你可以當點心來吃的荷果種
it's all oil
它都屬於油類
But it must be the lotus seed in the oil
但是必須是油類裡面的荷果種子
such food and drink
這樣的食物跟飲品
So tea is a drink
所以茶是一種飲品
That will provide phytochemicals
那都是會提供植化素的
so apart from what we know
所以除了我們知道的
fiber nutrients minerals
纖維 營養素 礦物之外
There is also a so-called phytochemical
還有一種所謂的植化素
it will be provided
它都是會提供的
So what kind of protein is it with?
那麼搭配的是哪一種的蛋白質呢
You can see these proteins
這些蛋白質你一看就知道
is less saturated fat
是飽和脂肪比較少的
We all know that saturated fat causes inflammation
大家都知道飽和脂肪是會致發炎
when the body is aging
就是老化的時候身體
I just talked about the body having a low-grade inflammation
我剛剛講到身體有一種低度發炎狀態
then this will affect
那這個都會影響到
Your body's protein synthesis
你的身體的蛋白質的合成
this low
這個低度
So it is a less protective fat
所以它是一個保護脂肪少
And it seems that the cover is quite rich
而且好像都是蓋質還蠻豐富
Cover quality of excuse class
藉口類的蓋質
cap quality of milk
和奶類的蓋質
these of fish
魚類的這些
The cap quality is relatively rich
的蓋質還算稍微豐富的
some proteins
的一些蛋白質類
Everyone knows about the fish
那魚的話大家都知道
middle of fish especially raw sea fish
魚的中間特別是生海魚
its omega
它的Omega
3 omega 3 fish oil is also anti-inflammatory
3 omega 3的這個魚油也是抗發炎
So this combination is actually very, very reasonable.
所以這樣的組合其實是非常非常的合理
a combination of
的一個組合
OK, so according to the information just now
OK所以呢按照剛剛那些資訊
Let's sort it out and look at it like this
我們把它整理再這樣子來看一下
It is for the prevention and treatment of senile Mohr disease
就是對於防治老齡酩柔症的
Tips for this diet
這個飲食的提示
The first we found was
第一個我們發現就是
Moech disease is a variety of nutrients
酩柔症都是有多種營養素
The condition of low intake
攝取偏低的狀況
but other than protein
但是除了蛋白質以外的
These other ones we don't really know who is a key factor
其他這些我們真的不知道誰是一個關鍵因素
Why do proteins know
蛋白質為什麼會知道
Because of years of research and interventions
因為多年的研究而且都做了介入
It means you are weak and I will give you protein
就是說你你衰弱我給你蛋白質
You see if there is such a study
你看看會不會好有這樣的一個這種研究
There is a lot of research on the headlines of this course protein
有這個當然蛋白質的頭語的很多研究
not so sure
也不是這麼樣的肯定
But this direction is relatively certain
但是這個方向是比較確定的
So the only way is to do an intervention study
所以唯一的方法就是做介入研究
That is to say, what you observe is sexual
也就是說你觀察到是性上
you put this
你把這個
Such a thing is given to the feeble
這樣的一個東西就給予衰弱的人
Let's see if he eats well
看看他吃了會不會好
that's the only thing that can be proven
那是唯一能夠證實的
So, from the information on the diet form just now,
那所以呢我們從剛剛這個飲食形態的資料
We're just thinking if
我們就是在想說如果
We follow this in the daily dietary guidelines
我們就按照每日飲食指南的這個
This way of taking a balanced diet is recommended for the elderly
攝取均衡的這個方式來建議給老人
What if he does this?
他如果做到這樣子的話呢
he just made sure
他就先確保說
Nutrients up to standard
營養素達標
Contains protein will hit the mark
包含蛋白質會達標
Of course the low calorie one
那當然那個低熱量的
We're going to tweak the protein
我們要把它蛋白質調一下
Then his overall nutritional status improved
那他整體營養狀況改善
that might be beneficial
那可能就有利於
whole body system
整體的生理系統的
Maintenance of function and muscle mass
機能跟肌肉量的維持
That's a hypothesis we made
那就是我們做的一個假說
Of course it means just this
當然就是說剛剛這個
The premise of our hypothesis is that
我們這個假說的前提就是說
there is an important
有個重要的
Requirements are more than 1500 calories
要件就是說1500大卡以上
Protein is really okay
蛋白質確實沒有問題
But what if it's under 1500 calories?
但是如果是1500大卡以下的話呢
still need to make some adjustments
還要做一些調整
I'm going to make some adjustments
我要去做一些調整
so we are
所以我們就在
Published in 2018
2018年發表一篇
Proof-of-principle interventional studies
原則驗證介入性研究
Just put the principle
就是把剛剛那個原則
put it in for a discussion
放進去做了一個探討
designed an experiment
設計了一個實驗
I will first talk about the results of this experiment
我先講這個實驗的結果
Then I will say that this experiment is
然後我再講這個實驗是
tell the old man how to eat
告訴老人怎麼吃的
So you can refer to
所以大家可以參考一下
talk about it first
先講一下
It is at the Miaoli Hospital of the Ministry of Health and Welfare
就是在衛生福利部苗栗醫院
we ask them to refer some
我們請他們轉介一些
After a little certification, the old man gave us an interventional study
稍微證了老人給我們去做介入研究
Then this study is a small study
那這個研究是一個很小的研究
Later we expanded it
後來我們又把它擴大
that in this study
那在這這個研究
Then we divided the elderly into the control group
然後我們就把老人分成對照組
do nothing
什麼都不做的
give him some vitamin mineral powder
給他一些維生素礦物脂粉的
And give him vitamin mineral powder
還有給他維生素礦物脂粉
and protein powder
以及蛋白脂粉的
There is dietary intervention
還有就是飲食介入
It was found that other
結果發現其他的
like protein powder
像即便給了蛋白脂粉
He's also helpful.
他效果也都有幫助啦
a little help
一點點幫助
But the real best is the food
但是真正最好的就是食物的
an intervention
一個介入
I dropped his score from 1.4 to
他這個分數我從1.4降到
0.77 means that
0.77的意思是這樣
Almost down 0.50 0.6
差不多降了0.50 0.6
he means to say
他的意思就是說
In fact, these old people are not too serious.
其實這些老人也不是太嚴重的
he just has 1 or 2
他就是有1到2個
Such an old man with thick asthenia
衰弱症厚的这样的老人
We can say that 50% of them are elderly
我们可以说其中有50%的老人
He lost one symptom
他减少了一个症厚
Because his score dropped around 0.6
因为他的分数下降了0.6左右
probably so
大概是这样
He is remarkable for having such an effect
他是显著的有这样的一个效果
In addition, we also measured the depression of old age.
另外就是我们还测了老年的忧郁
This is also found
发现也是这一种
He will have a better mood
他会有一个心情比较好的一个现象
see this phenomenon
看到这样的现象
This is what we used in a small study
这是我们用一个小型的研究
publish it first
先把它发表了
Then we did it again
之后我们又进行了
This is also the sustainable plan of Academia Sinica
这也是中研院永续计划
We conduct a large study
我们进行一个大型的研究
just a little more crowded
就是比较多人一点
There are about 300 people
就是大概有接近300人
4% main
4%主
At this time, it is also paired with exercise
这时候还搭配了运动
It is the master of contrast and the master of movement
就是对照主 运动主
Nutrition master and nutritionist exercise master
营养主跟营养家 运动主
Our intervention is
我们这个介入是
Take a Nutritional Counseling
采用一种营养咨询
Coordination and physical fitness consultation
搭配还有体能的咨询
Then let the old man go home and do it himself
然后让老人回家自己做
how to make him like this
让他这样子的做法
as far as we found
就我们发现
That's the control group is blue
就是這對照組是藍色
Then sports nutrition in different colors
然後運動營養不同顏色
Can see the drop in this sour score
可以看到這個酸弱的分數的下降
There is a downward trend
下降有一種降的下降趨勢
And the nutrition group is slightly better than the exercise group
而且是營養組比運動組略好
Nutrition plus exercise group is best
營養加運動組最好
such a phenomenon
這樣的一個現象
The article here is currently being revised
那這邊文章現在正在修改
Submitted papers should be accepted
已經投稿出去應該會被接受
that's a very cheap step in
那是一個非常便宜的介入
That is to say, it will not cost the country too much money to intervene
就是說不會花國家太多錢的介入
I have seen such an effect
有看到這樣的一個效果
What about this?
那這樣子的話呢
I'm coming to tell you
我就來跟大家講
But how much did we change
但是我們到底做了多少改變
In fact, very small changes are not very big
其實非常小的改變不是很大的
So maybe I'll stop here a little bit now
所以可能我現在在這邊稍微停下來講一下
Most people might think that
一般人可能都會認為說
I have vegetables and I have fruits
我有吃蔬菜我有吃水果
You asked me to eat the whole stock, and I also ate it.
你叫我吃全股我也有吃啊
You said I would eat with wheat
你說帶麥子我也吃啊
Then why is my health not as good as yours
那為什麼我的健康就沒你的好
for example
要譬如說
like my words me personally
像我的話 我個人
should be inside our lock
應該在我們鎖裡面
I'm pretty healthy
我算是身體蠻不錯的
But the bento I make with everyone every day
可是我每天跟大家都一起做的那吃便當
that difference
那個差別
That small difference means
那個小小的差別就是說
Now this bento
現在這個便當
I looked over and said
我一眼看過去就說
too few vegetables
蔬菜太少
There is enough protein, why is the rice white rice?
蛋白足夠 飯怎麼是白飯
That's what I've got in mind
我心裡就這樣盤算了
So I'm going to correct it
所以我會去校正啊
i go home at night
我晚上回家
I just eat back the vegetables I don't have enough
我就把我不夠的蔬菜吃回來了
The fruit I didn't have enough also came back
我不夠的水果也吃回來了
Then he gave me rice
然後他給我白飯
I might just take a little of that for myself
我可能就自己帶一點那個
Sprinkle that wheat germ tooth powder on it
那個小麥胚牙粉撒上去
I'll just make a small change
我就做一點小小的改變
Your body is different from others
你的身體就跟人家不一樣
so look over here
所以你看這邊
Control group Exercise group Nutrition group
控制組 運動組 營養組
These four groups look at the first point
這四個組 你看第一點
Whole stock and shoulder amine is rice
全股跟肩胺就是飯
Everyone still has three months of hard work
大家都還是經過三個月的功夫
Nothing has changed, everyone eats the same
沒什麼改變 大家都吃得一樣
but the previous one
但是前面這個
This is the control group and the exercise group
這個是對照組跟運動組
Its protein hasn't changed either.
它的這個蛋白質也沒什麼改變
but look
但是你看
It's the nutrition group, it's called the nutrition exercise group.
就是營養組 叫做營養運動組
its increased protein
它的蛋白質增加
increased by half
增加了半份
Half portion seems to be rare, right?
半份好像很少對不對
But it adds half after all
但它畢竟增加了半份
Then its milk increased by 60cc
然後它的牛奶增加了60cc
So these two things
所以這兩個東西
Turns out you know we test these guys
結果你知道我們測這些人
the egg in it
它尿裡面的那個蛋
Because there is nitrogen in the protein
因為蛋白質裡面有nitrogen
The urine egg in it is a significant increase
它裡面的尿蛋就是顯著的增加
For acid shock
對於酸藥震
Urinary egg means more protein is more important
尿蛋就是蛋白質測多就是重要
just add a little bit
才加這麼一點點
it's ok
就可以了
Everyone eats fruits and vegetables
水果蔬菜大家都吃差不多
also slightly increased
也都略為增加了一點點
Nutrients
水果的話是營養組
Probably added 0.3 servings of fruit
大概增加了0.3份水果
But there is another interesting thing
但是還有一個很有趣的就是
because we gave them lotus
因為我們給它們提供了荷果
so they added a portion and a half a day
所以它們一天增加了一份半
That is, the fruit of the hour and a half
也就是一時半的荷果
These are the old people who eat an extra tablespoon a year
就是這些老人每年會多吃一湯匙的
all kinds of lotus
各種的那種荷果
like some almonds and so on mixed together
像什麼杏仁啊什麼等等混在一起的
Also because of their increased protein
另外因為它們的蛋白質增加
It will also increase the oil of the half food
它也會增加了半食的油
It may be necessary for spray toughness
就是可能噴韌會需要的
So you think about this for a while
那所以你想一時半的這個
Calories in wagashi
和果的熱量
Just push it up a little bit
就把它的熱量推上去了一些
protein also pushed up
蛋白質也推上去
just such a small change
就這麼一點的改變
Let these old people burn their meat
就讓這些老人的燒肉症
get a big one
得到很大的一個
So what I want to tell you now is
所以我現在這一點要跟大家講的就是
a little fine-tuning
一點點的微調喔
so you and the guy next door
所以你跟你隔壁的人
You see you eat almost everything
你看你們東西都吃差不多
Why is one in shape and the other in poor health?
為什麼一個身條一個身體不好
The bad thing is this
差的就是這一點點
But this thing for the general public
但是這個東西對一般民眾
If it wasn't for everyone coming here today
今天要不是大家來這裡
to the general public
對一般民眾
I want to talk to him face to face
我要面對面跟他講
He doesn't even want to listen
他都不願意不見得要聽啊
you know what i mean
你你知道我意思
so you take care of yourself now
所以你現在要照顧自己
it's not easy for you
你也不容易做到
So I'm going to tell you about a software
所以我等一下要跟大家講一個軟體
You can go in and carefully consider what you eat.
你可以進去仔細的推敲一下自己吃的
worse than that standard
差那個標準
It's a little bit worse, you can change it
差的那麼一點點你把它改一下
it will be of great help
就會有很大的一個幫助了
ok this is over here
好這個就是這邊就是
This paper only mentions that
這張紙只是提到就是說
If you are someone with different calories
如果你是有不同熱量的人
Together
一起
1300 14000 15000 1600 to this
1300 14000 15000 1600到這個的話
You see, the amount of meals everyone eats is slightly different every day
你看每個人每天吃的飯的量是略有不同
Your protein will go up slowly
你的這個蛋白質就要慢慢慢慢上去了
vegetables fruit and
蔬菜 水果 還有
our word in taiwan
我們在台灣的話
Our suggested dairy class is stable
我們的建議的乳品類是穩定的
no increase
沒有增加
But on protein and protein
但是在蛋白質跟蛋白質上去的
There is a scaling like this
都有一個scaling這樣子上去
Then like this grease also goes up
然後像這個油脂也是有上去
So this data is hard to remember.
所以這個數據很難記啦
So you have to put your own data in
所以你一定要把自己的數據輸進去
then find your combination
然後找到你的組合
you just write it down
你就把它記下來
keep for reference
留著隨時參考
like this
要這個樣子
to do this
要這樣做
then we are at the place of intervention
那我們在那個介入的場所
how do we do it
我們是怎麼做的呢
Then this step means that everyone can do it too.
那這個步驟等於就是各位也可以
A practice that you can follow
自己可以follow的一個做法
That is, after you see us coming in alone
就是你看我們一個人進來之後
let's see first
我們先看看
How tall and how heavy is he?
由他有多 身高多高 體重多重
is he male or female how old is he
他是男的是女的是幾歲
we'll know
我們就會知道說
How many calories should this person eat
這個人他應該吃多少熱量
I know how many calories he eats when
我知道他吃多少熱量的時候
I know how much he should eat
我就知道他該吃多少飯
How much meat and how much vegetables
多少肉多少菜
Just know how much oil and how much fruit
多少油多少水果就知道
We have such a data
我們就有這麼一個數據
then this time
然後這個時候呢
we'll ask this guy
我們就會問問這個人
that is, how do you usually eat
就是說你平常是怎麼吃的
he described
他就描述
After the description, we immediately recorded it on the computer.
描述之後我們就立刻用電腦記錄下來
If you type a software, it will show his appearance.
打到一個軟體就算出來他的樣
the appearance of what he eats
他吃的東西的樣貌
If it's not enough, ask him to make it up
不夠的就叫他補
After that we'll give him a personal prescription
之後呢我們就會給他一個個人處方
This personal prescription is very important
這個個人處方是非常重要的
It just feels like a watch
就是感覺上好像就一個表
But everyone knows that eating is an art.
可是大家知道吃東西是一個藝術啊
That is to say, you eat like this
就是說你吃東西是這樣吃進去
he eats like that
他吃東西是那樣子吃進去
I can't always tell you
我總不能去告訴你說
how many servings how many servings
吃多少份多少份多少份
Then you won't do it when you go back
那你回去還是不會做
So when we intervene
所以我們在介入的時候呢
we have personal
我們有跟針對個人
discuss with him
跟他討論
Just to see where he can change the most easily
就是看他哪裡可以最容易改
Just changed him like this
就把他這樣改掉了
is such a way
是這樣的一種的方式
In fact, it is not easy to do interventional research.
其實做介入研究非常的不容易
He just knows he probably doesn't want to do it
他就是知道了他可能也不想做
so intervening
所以在介入
We also need to start talking to him about
我們還要開始跟他討論說
Hey, do you know you have debilitating disease?
欸 你知不知道你有衰弱症啊
Hey, do you know what frailty is?
欸 你知道衰弱症是什麼東西嗎
Then he went to the hospital to test
然後他到醫院去試驗
He couldn't walk so he went to the hospital
他走不動路 所以他去醫院
He would have liked the doctor to help him
他本來希望醫生給他幫忙
But the doctor can't help with this disease
但是這個症醫生是沒有辦法幫忙的
So the doctor referred him to us
所以醫生把他轉介到我們這邊來
then we told him
然後我們就跟他說
Do you know your weakness
你知不知道你這個衰弱
is replyable
是可以回復的
but you have to cooperate with us
但是你要跟我們配合
you only need to eat nutrition
你只要吃的營養
you can reply
你就是有可以回復
After gaining such a trust from him
得到他的這樣的一個信任之後
We'll just tell him what to do after that
我們就告訴他應該怎樣之後呢
After talking about how you should eat
講完說你應該怎麼吃
How to eat how to eat, then you have to ask him
怎麼吃怎麼吃 然後就要問他說
Will you have trouble doing this?
你這樣子做會不會有困難呢
He told people that he had difficulties
他就跟人家說有困難啊
Because I don't cook the food at home
因為家裡飯不是我煮的
Or it means that my family usually buys this kind of thing
或者是說我通常家人就是買這種東西
Then we're going to work it out with him.
然後我們就要跟他一起去解決
these questions
這些問題
Then these problems are also encountered by everyone.
那這些問題也是各位都會碰到的
You may have listened to the speech today and you go back and want to change it
你今天可能聽完演講你回去想改
But your food is not made by you at all
可是你們家菜根本就不是你做的
so you have to talk to your family
所以你必須要跟你家
the other half
另外一半
your child
你的小孩
or your family
或者是你們家的
Who is in charge to do a consultation
誰負責的人來做一個商量
discuss
商量
of course we have
我們當然還有
It depends on the level of understanding of Hirao's case.
要平良這個個案的理解程度啦
he has some unhappy things
他有一些不高興的事情
Let's let him vent his emotions, wait
我們讓他釋放他的情緒啊等等
A methodology for nutrition education with a few, many
用一些很多的這個營養教育的一個方法學
to do
來做
Then track after the first month
然後第一個月之後會追蹤
A methodology for repeating these nutrition education
再重複這些營養教育的一個方法學
Ping Liang then let him release his emotions
平良然後讓他釋放情緒
Build a supportive relationship with him
跟他建立支援關係
Think of alternatives with him
跟他一起想代替方案
then one month to three months
然後一個月到三個月
We also gave him some rewards
我們還給他一些獎勵
Sign some consent forms with him too.
也跟他一起簽一些同意書啊
Say I'm willing to change like this
說我願意這樣來改變啊什麼
There are many methodologies in this
這都有很多的方法學在裡面
Well then I'll be next
那好我下面就
start talking about this
開始講一下這個
A tool we used at the time
我們當時用的一個工具啊
We used a standard dinner plate
我們是用了一個標準餐盤
what about this plate
那這個餐盤呢
is available
是可以買得到的
this plate is
這個餐盤是
if you are interested
如果你有興趣的話
You can go online to Tang Diabetes Association
你可以上網到唐尿病衛教學會
Maybe three or four hundred yuan.
可能三四百塊這樣一個
Then its easy thing to do is
然後它很容易的事情就是
it has three holes on this side
它這邊有三個洞
if you should have one
如果你該吃一份
you should eat four
你該吃四份
If you have a few copies, you can fill it up.
幾份的話你就把它填滿就好了
Then this place is two servings of vegetables
然後這個地方是兩份蔬菜
so it's one meal at a time
所以它是一餐一餐的
such a plan
這樣的一個規劃
then here
然後這邊
here is
這邊就是
This city meeting is the location of rice
這個市議是飯的位置
fruit location
水果的位置
location of milk
奶類的位置
oil location
油的位置
Each of our nutritionists
我們的每一個營養師
We designed this for him
都我們幫他設計的這樣一份
This person will tell the nutritionist
這個人就會告訴營養師
say what i eat
說我吃什麼什麼什麼
The nutritionist probably drew a picture
營養師就大概畫了一畫
i found this guy
我發現這個人
It's all protein
這個上面都是蛋白質
six servings of protein
六份蛋白質
this is his night
這個是他晚上
I will eat so many dishes at noon
中午會吃這麼多的菜
Such a dish at night
晚上是這麼菜
he has two servings of vegetables
他有兩份的蔬菜
His meal looks like this
他的飯大概這樣子
how much milk does he drink
他喝牛奶多少
he has fried ham
他有煎了火腿
This ham dish is a bit oily
這個火腿的菜有點油
fried vegetables with oil
炒青菜有油
he's like that
他就這麼樣的
after evaluating it
把它評估了之後
There is a number here
這邊就有一個數字
this number
這個數字
This number can be compared with this person's
這個數字就可以跟這個人的
actually
實際上
Take it and check it
攝取的去對一下
What about after matching?
配完了之後呢
we might just tell it again
我們可能就再告訴它說
Your next three meals will be divided like this
你的以後三餐就這樣分配好了
you have a glass of milk in the morning
你早上要喝一杯牛奶
eat two slices of toast
吃兩片吐司
It is best to have a toast with some lotus fruit
最好是個吐司能夠搭配一些荷果
Whether it is placed separately or
不論是另外放的或者是
It's fruit toast
就是荷果吐司
Two servings of Chinese food
那中餐的話兩份
a bit of meat and an egg
有一點肉 有一個蛋
then two servings of vegetables
然後兩份蔬菜
Served with whole bone rice and a fruit
搭配全骨飯 有一個水果
Then you can also pair a
那你還可以搭配一個
This dessert is like a yogurt for dessert
這個甜點 類似甜點的一個優格
Then dinner is two protein courses
然後晚餐是兩道蛋白質
A dish like this
一道菜 這樣子
a piece of fruit a whole bone meal
一份水果 一個全骨飯
Just help it make a plan like this
就幫它做了一個這樣的規劃
For example, a person eats a lot
這個譬如說有個人吃很多的
2100 kcal
2100大卡
it even has protein in the morning
它甚至早上就有蛋白質
I ate porridge in the morning, etc.
早上吃的是粥等等
It is also a plan like this
也是類似這樣的一個規劃
so a dinner plate like this
所以像這樣的餐盤
You can also use this to help you
大家也可以用這個來幫助你
For example, you should eat
譬如說你該吃到
For example, four servings of protein
譬如說四份的蛋白質
That's four servings, about
這就是四份 大概是
has an auxiliary effect
有一個輔助的一個功效
So in our study just now
所以我們在剛剛那個研究當中
Just use the same method just now for the nutritionist to use
就用剛剛那樣的一個方式給營養師來使用
what about this plate
這個餐盤呢
We also sent each case a copy
我們還送了每個個案一人一份
and we put food models on the plate
而且我們把餐盤上放了食物模型
This is 500 calories
這個是500大卡
Maybe a plate with 700 kcal
可能700大卡的一個裝盤的樣子
We also gave it fruit and milk powder
我們還送了它和果跟奶粉
Because it was done in the Miaoli area
因為當時在苗栗地區做
People in Miaoli do not drink milk powder very much
苗栗地區的人都不太喝奶粉
And he is not used to buying wagashi
而且他也沒有習慣買和果
so we want to say
所以我們想說
It's better to send them when we start to intervene
我們開始介入的時候最好是送他們
Otherwise he might just listen
不然他可能聽聽就算了
So this is sending
所以這個是正送
so that he can remember
那為了讓他能夠記得
We also designed a restaurant
我們還設計了一個餐店
Let him take this restaurant home
這個餐店就讓他拿回家
This is the size of a normal restaurant
這個就是一般的那個餐店那麼大
put him on the table
讓他放在桌上
So he knows that 500 calories will look like this
所以他知道500大卡就長這個樣子
His family can also see
他的家人也可以看到
His plate should look like this
他的盤子應該這樣裝
That 600 calories looks like this
那600大卡就長這個樣子
So you can see that the difference is very small
所以你看這個差異非常的少
but everyone is different
可是每一個人都是不一樣的
Then here are some references
那這邊還有一些參考
five hundred six hundred seven hundred and eight hundred
五百六百七百八百
That's a very small drawing
那這個是畫得很小
Make some reference for his family
給他的家人做一些參考
But every old man wants to
但是每一個老人他要
His meal might look like this
他的一餐可能是長這個樣子
OK so
OK 所以
This is how we intervene
這個就是我們的介入方法
but i'm going to talk a little bit about this
但是我要稍微講一下這個
This section provides individual prescriptions
提供個人處方的這一塊
Because everyone eats differently
因為每一個人的吃飯的方法不一樣
we will encounter many problems
我們會碰到很多的問題
For example, some people
譬如說有一些人
he just doesn't drink milk
他就是不喝牛奶的
For example, we have to discuss with him
譬如說我們就要跟他商量
There was an old man who said
有一個老人他說
I drink three in one in the morning
我早上都喝三合一
he speaks like this
他就這樣子講
I drink three in one
我都是喝三合一的
then we know he likes coffee
那我們就知道他喜歡喝咖啡
so i told him
所以我告訴他說
Then why don't you go and buy some coffee powder?
那你好不好去買一個咖啡粉
buy more brown sugar
再買一點紅糖
buy another can of milk powder
再買一罐奶粉
you put the three together
你把這三個搭起來
It's very similar to your three-in-one
跟你的三合一很像啊
we'll make the suggestion
我們就會做這樣的建議
Some people say I just don't eat fruit
有人說我就是不吃水果
then you have to find a way
那你要想個辦法
then would you like
那你願不願意
For example, some dried fruit
譬如說有一些果乾
These things can also be replaced
這些東西也可以取代啊
raisins or something
葡萄乾啊 或什麼
Or really don't want to eat
或者是實在不願意吃
100% fruit juice though not the best
百分之百果汁 雖然不是最好
is also an applied method
也是 也是一個應用的方法
it lacks protein
它蛋白質量不足
Like, for example, I came across a case
像譬如說我碰過一個個案
Of course, I'm not there to intervene there every day.
當然我不是自己天天在那邊做介入
I run over every week to have a look
我是每個禮拜會跑過去看一下
When encountering a case, it will tell me
碰到一個個案它就跟我說
I have three highs, what protein do I eat?
我都三高我吃什麼蛋白質
Then we have to tell it with evidence
那我們就要用實證跟它講說
various scientific displays
各種科學顯示
Protein can not only lower blood pressure
蛋白質不但可以降血壓
Can also help control your blood sugar
也可以幫助你血糖的控制
If you're eating the right kind of protein
如果你蛋白質的種類吃得對的話
red meat
如果不創紅肉
If there are more tofu and fish
如果是比較多的豆腐跟魚的話
Because cholesterol doesn't rise either
因為膽固醇也不會上升
talk to it
要跟它講
some people have too much protein
那有些人又蛋白質過多
if too much
過多的話呢
You have to change the form of the dish
你就要讓它菜的形式改變
For example, I always like big pieces of meat.
譬如說本來我都喜歡大塊肉的
Now you may have some dishes that use shredded pork
那現在你可能有些菜是要用肉絲來做
as delicious
一樣好吃啊
So these are negotiable
所以這些都是要商量的
where to buy
包含何果哪裡買
And some people are health conscious
還有有些人是健康意識
All dishes are hot
什麼菜都用燙的
We also have to tell it that this is not good
我們也要告訴它說這樣子不好的
you still have to use oil
你還是要用油
to cook because of the oil
來炒菜 因為油
Provides calories for the elderly and has a full vitamin coat
提供老人熱量 而且有很充分的維他麵衣
It's a good thing, why don't I use it all?
這是一個好東西啊 為什麼我全部不用呢
It's wrong to cook all dishes hot
什麼菜都用燙的 這是不對的
So these kinds of questions are different for everyone.
所以這些各式各樣的問題 每一個人的問題都不一樣
You have to break them one by one.
你要一一擊破 這樣子才行
So dietary intervention is really not easy
那所以飲食介入真的是很不容易
if not do
如果不會做的話
We saw many people on Wenyan
我們看到文艷上很多人
After teaching people how to eat, there is no effect at all
教人家怎麼吃之後 一點效果都沒有
Just because he not only needs to know the prescription
就是因為他不但是要知道處方
And also, that prescription needs to be personalized.
而且還要 那個處方還要個人化
but also in line with his personal form
還要符合他個人的形態
So I guess this is when you guys go back
所以我想這是大家你們回去之後
a problem that everyone will face
都會面對的一個問題
Then this is what we ask the elderly to fill in every day
那這個就是我們讓老人每天要去填寫
how much did he eat
他這些東西吃了多少
When you fill in this every day
那這個每天填的時候
It also reminds him again and again that he must meet the standard.
也是一再的提醒他 他要達標
OK so we just told you about this
OK 所以我們剛剛跟大家講這種
How is he in terms of nutritional entry research?
營養進入的研究來說 他是怎麼樣呢
That is to say, there are many literatures that provide caloric supplements
就是說文獻上有很多的提供熱量補給
or protein calorie supplement
或者是蛋白質熱量補給的
This kind of research generally tends to be good
這種研究一般來說是趨向好的
but not exactly the same
但是不是完全的一致
Generally speaking, if this type of
通常來講如果這種類型的
Recording research if paired with exercise
紀錄研究如果搭配了運動
Usually there are more positive effects
通常有正向效應的比較多
But from our records study we found that
但是由我們的紀錄研究我們發現
If the principle of balanced diet
如果用均衡飲食原則
Interventions that Provide Personalized Nutrition
提供個人化的營養的介入
in the case of supplements such as it
在如果提供它這樣的補充品的話
what we feel it is
我們感覺它的是
We found that it is possible to improve
我們發現是能夠改善
Overall nutritional status Post-fall status and level of depression
整體營養狀態 摔後狀態以及憂鬱的程度
and we have other single use nutrients
而且我們有其他的單一使用營養素的
This supplement is not as effective as the food itself
這種補充品效果就沒有食物本身來的好
This is one of our record research
這是我們的一個紀錄研究
come to such a conclusion
得到這樣的一個結論
OK, after this point
OK 講到這邊之後呢
Then there is another issue of geriatric syndrome, which is
那還有另外一個老年症候群的議題就是
Dementia
失智這一塊
We started to do this
這一塊我們開始做了
But in this so-called observation belief
但是在這個所謂的這個觀察信念就
This step in data mining
資料採礦的這個步驟
Let me do some simple summary for you
我來跟大家做一些簡單的這個 summary
That is, first of all, we take a look and we find that
就是首先我們看一下就是我們發現
this so-called short intelligence test for the elderly
老年人的這個所謂的這個簡短的智能測驗
There is a short test called MMSC
有一個叫 MMSC 這樣的一個簡短的測驗
It can measure all aspects of the intelligence of the elderly
它可以測老人的這個智能的各面相
Then we have done something like this in Nutrition University
那我們在營養大學都有做這樣一個東西
We found that starting at age 65
我們發現就是從65歲開始
This intelligence will fall down
這個智能就往下掉
male female or overall
男性 女性或者是整體
we use this score
我們就使用這個分數
Come do some diet research with this
來去做一些飲食的這個研究
that's in constitution
那在文憲上
If we look at the International Constitution, we find
我們如果去看國際文憲發現
There are quite a lot of nutrients that are closely related to Shi Zhi
這個跟施至息息相關的營養素也是蠻多的
Contains Vitamin B Complex Vitamin C Vitamin E Vitamin D
包含了維生素B群 維生素C 維生素E 維生素D
There are also various plant chemicals
還有各種植化素
Then it's not the same as this debility
那它就跟這個衰弱不一樣
Debilitating many clinical trials are doing protein
衰弱很多的臨床試驗都在做蛋白質
But Shi Zhi's research is very little
但是施至的研究呢非常的少
And it's all small
而且都是小小
research, now it is found that there are several studies
研究 那現在發現就是有幾個研究
Such research on delaying cognitive decline
對於延緩認知功能衰退的這樣的研究
Effective research finds almost all in mild cognitive impairment
有效的研究發現幾乎都在輕度認知功能障礙
It's just that it's starting to drop a little bit
就是它開始分數有點下降
If it's serious, it's almost useless
如果說是很嚴重了 幾乎是沒有什麼效果
So this demented anti-intelligence is to find
所以這個失智的防智的話就是要找
If it is too late, at most it will stop thinking and it won't get worse
如果晚的話最多是讓它停智 不會惡化
There is one study that is the most significant
那有一個研究是最顯著的研究
What it shows is that it can be almost with relative certainty
它顯現的就是可以幾乎可以比較確定
It is the intervention of vitamin B group
就是維生數B群的介入
vitamin B group it has several B
維生數B群它有好幾個B
Like 8 folic acid Vitamin B2 Vitamin B6
像8很葉酸 維生數B2 維生數B6
These are all related to the synthesis of our neurotransmitters
這幾個全部都跟我們的神經傳導物質的合成有關
Then this group B research is done
那這個B群的研究是做的
There is a group B study my current author's name I forgot
有一個B群研究 我現在的作者名字我忘掉
They do it very carefully and they use MR
做得非常的講究 他們是用MR
To measure the volume of the brain
去測腦部的這個體積
It was found that the head and nose group can significantly slow down this atrophy
結果發現頭與鼻群可以顯著的減緩這個萎縮
It is now the only study in the world
現在是國際上唯一的一個研究
This is what works great
這個就是這個有很好的效果
But we believe that influencing this
但是我們相信影響這個
There are many factors for this dementia
這個失智的因素很多了
just say it cuts in with nutrients
只是說它用營養素的切入的話
is to see the nose group
是看到鼻群
there are many more
還有很多的
Now there are actually a lot of this
現在目前其實有很多的這個
Industry is
Industry就是
Industry is called industry, it should be called manufacturer
Industry就是叫工業應該叫廠商
now i know
現在我知道
Because I participated in a Shi Zhi Certification Conference in Europe last year
因為我去年參加歐洲的一個施志證會
They are developing some silver products
他們在開發一些銀品
Some silver items to see if they can help Shi Zhi
一些銀品看看對能不能夠幫助施志
There must be nose groups in that silver product.
那個銀品裡面都一定有鼻群
But with a lot of other things
但還搭配了很多其他的東西
so this
所以這個
Then our laboratory is currently working on a mineral
那我們實驗室目前也有在做一個礦物質
Look at its relationship with this dementia
看它跟這個失智的一個關係
OK, what about the nutritional health survey?
OK 那在營養健康調查呢
I also found that it was with this lion
也發現就是跟這個獅子
It's the people with low MMSC scores
就是MMSC的分數很低的這些人呢
He's basically a lot of stuff
他就基本上就是很多東西相關
very low heat
就熱量特別的偏低
Protein fat with carbohydrates B1 B2 B
蛋白質脂肪連碳水化物B1 B2 B
B3 is nice B6 B1 CDE
B3就是nice B6 B1 CDE
Fake calcium core iron
假鈣美芯靈鐵
Fatty acids regardless of saturated units
脂肪酸不論飽和單元多元
low cholesterol
膽固醇都偏低
low fiber
纖維偏低
So here is a phenomenon that appears when people get old
所以這邊顯現一個現象就是人到老的時候
Usually not all heart disease in the past
一般過去不是都心臟病
high cholesterol
膽固醇很高嗎
but by then
可是到那個時候
You have heart disease and high cholesterol
你就是心臟病膽固醇高
At that time, it was not high anymore. They all came down.
那個時候也不高了 都下來了
So this time is to eat more
所以這個時候就是要多吃
To eat more is a key point
要多吃是一個重點
So this is already entering another
所以這已經是進入另外一個
a question from the era
紀元的一個問題
What about diet?
那麼飲食型態方面呢
A little more research room
研究室稍微多一點
other than the mediterranean diet
它除了地中海飲食之外
There is another one called Deshu Diet
還有一個叫德書飲食
this is the famous
這個是那個有名的
Our Blood Pressure Diet
我們的降血壓飲食
And these two combinations
還有就是這兩個組合
It is built by the Mediterranean Sea. The English name is Mediterranean.
就是地中海搭造英文叫Mediterranean
Teshu diet called Dash
德樹飲食叫Dash
Just M and D
就M加D
It's the Maddie diet
就是麥德飲食形態
All three have been seen
這三個都已經看到
Protective effect on cognitive function
對認知功能有保護的效果
but basically forward-looking
但基本上都是前瞻的
is now to measure you have a diet like this
就是現在測量你有這樣的飲食
You won't lose your mind easily
以後你不容易失智
like this
是這樣子
What this diet emphasizes is
那這種飲食強調的就是
Whole fruit and fruit seeds
蔬果全果和果種子
milk tea
奶蛋 茶飲
everyone looks like
大家看起來跟
Acid meat disease is a bit like
酸肉症的有點像
but not exactly the same
但是不是完全一樣
There are milk eggs here, have you seen it?
就這邊有奶蛋有沒有看到
Just Acid Meat Syndrome has no dairy eggs at all
剛剛酸肉症完全沒有奶蛋
Just sour flesh is the synthesis of muscle
剛剛酸肉症是肌肉的合成
are all fish
都是魚
Shelfish is
Shelfish就是
borrow class
藉可類
seafood
海鮮
something like this
這樣的東西
The same is the tea
一樣的就是這個茶飲
This is what the West sees
這是西方國家看到的
then we Taiwan
那麼我們台灣
We also published an article
我們也發表了一篇文章
is the most 2018
就是最2018
It seems that only recently 2018 is an electronic file
好像最近才2018是電子檔
This is that Galliproof is the draft
這個是那個Galliproof就是草稿
is the first edition of typesetting
就是排版的第一版
Later, it should be a study that came out at the beginning of this year.
後來是應該是今年年初出來的一個研究
We are referring to the nutritional adjustment data
我們就是說把營養調校的資料
It's always been said that if your score is demented
不斷是看說如果你的分數失智的
just have this dementia score
就是有這個失智的分數
how is your diet
你的飲食怎麼樣
Let's look at what you ate twenty years ago
我們還看說你在二十年前吃的東西
relationship with subsequent dementia
跟後來失智的關係
To do this this paper brings together two studies
做這個這篇論文集合了兩種研究
As a result, we see that we divide men and women separately
結果看到我們分男女性分開來看
All found this rich image of diet type factor
都找到這個富像的飲食型態因子
In terms of integration, of course, the sequence is a little different.
結果整合來講當然順序有一點不同
In general, there are many fruits
整合來講就是水果多
Lots of vegetables, lots of lotus seeds, lots of whole fruits and miscellaneous grains
蔬菜多 荷果種子多 全果雜糧多
breakfast slices
早餐賣片
The most important thing is that Yan sells the film
最主要就是那個燕賣片
Eggs Dairy Seafood Tea & Coffee
蛋 乳類 海產 茶跟咖啡
This one looks like Shulton
這個看起來跟Shulton
Like the Maddie Diet with Shulton
跟Shulton像麥德飲食一樣
very much like frailty but you can see
非常像衰弱症 但是你可以看到
Egg
蛋
This appearance of the egg, the appearance of the milk egg
蛋的這個出現 奶蛋的出現
I want to say it's an interventional study with that group B.
我想說是跟那個B群的介入研究
There is a mutual echo, that is, the B group is related to the brain
有一點相互呼應 就是B群是跟腦子有關的
So the protein that comes out here will have eggs
所以這邊出來的蛋白質 就會有蛋出現
dairy comes out very clearly
乳品出現得非常清楚
Then there are also tea and coffee
那另外同樣的有茶跟咖啡
That tea and coffee are the same
那茶跟咖啡都是一個
Orthocarcin is very rich in Orthocarcin, which has antioxidant energy
直化素非常豐富的 就是有抗氧化能源的直化素
And there's some caffeine in it for a drink like this
而且有一些咖啡因 在裡面這樣的一個飲品
So after I see a result like this
所以我看到這樣的一個結果之後
I think the diet of the last group of the elderly can be integrated
我就覺得老年最後群的飲食是可以整合的
Because frailty is not that different from dementia
因為衰弱跟失智差別不是太大
It is these proteins that must be taken care of
就是這一些蛋白質類都要給它顧全到
it's probably almost
就可能差不多了
So what we just talked about in the dementia part is
所以我們剛剛在失智的這塊 我們講到的就是
We found that the caloric intake of elderly people with dementia is low
我們發現高齡失智者熱量都攝取偏低
Significantly lower levels of many trace elements
很多劇量的微量元素都有顯著較低的
Including those things that should not be high
包含那一些本來就不該高的東西
like cholesterol and saturated fat
像膽固醇跟飽和脂肪
Originally, we all said that it must be low and low.
本來我們都說一定要低要低的東西
Now both of those things are down too
現在這兩個東西也都低下來
also lowered
也都變低了
On the contrary, it means your cholesterol, but dont limit it
反倒就是說你膽固醇但也不要限制了
Don't limit the meat
肉也不要限制了
Because now it's just a matter of eating too little
因為現在就是吃太少的一個問題
What about the elderly with good cognitive function?
那麼認知功能好的這些高齡者呢
We just saw fresh fruit
我們剛剛看到就是新鮮水果
Wagyu whole milk protein rich food
和果全股奶類蛋白質豐富的食物
Like men are fish and sea bream
像男性是魚和海仔
Women are eggs or soy products
女性是蛋或黃豆類製品
and tea and coffee
還有就是喝茶跟咖啡
a form of sauce
醬構成的一個形態
So what we have in Taiwan is different from the international ones.
所以我們台灣的這個跟國際上的
is very consistent
是非常一致的
In addition, prospective studies
另外就是說前瞻性研究
I just talked about prospective studies
我剛剛有講前瞻性研究
we have another profile
我們有另外一個資料
found that 20 years ago in the 1990s
就發現說20年前1990年代
If these people happen to be
這些人如果正好是
If you like to eat fish and drink tea
喜歡吃魚也喜歡喝茶的話
He was in 2000 2010
他在2000年2010年
less risk of dementia
失智的風險就會比較小
So there is a long-term and a short-term
所以這個還有一個長期跟短期
there is a little different news
有一點點不一樣的消息
In the long run, it starts from middle age
長期來講就是從中年開始
Of course you want to prevent cardiovascular disease
你當然就是要預防心臟血管疾病
This kind of thing like three high
這種三高這樣的一個東西
let this risk down
讓這個風險下降
Then this I believe this plays such a role
那這個我相信這個扮演的是這樣一個角色
but in the short term
但是短期的話
You need to get enough nutrients
你要讓營養素充足
Group B is enough
B群要夠啦
enough protein
蛋白質要夠啦
tea or enough
喝茶啦或者要夠
These two are somewhat similar but
這個兩個有點類似但是
different face
不同的面向
so we just
所以我們就
Combining the above information?
結合這以上的資料呢
We're in the National Construction Agency's program
我們就在國建署的計畫裡面
we suggest
我們就建議說
The key to the prevention and treatment of geriatric syndrome
老年症候群防治的關鍵
Diet content
飲食內容
should mean
應該是就是說
The first point
第一點
You must balance the six categories
你一定要均衡的設入六大類
Then of course we have to deal with those who set up twelve
那麼當然要對於設十兩少的人
The allocation of these six categories should be adjusted
要把這六大類分配做一個調整
We must emphasize what I just said
我們必須強調我剛剛講的這些
Vegetables, Nuts, Seeds, Mushrooms, Milk
蔬果 堅果 種子 泉菇類 奶類
and protein-rich foods
以及蛋白質豐富的食物
with healthy tea
要搭配健康茶飲
In terms of protein, what is better for the elderly?
蛋白質的話是什麼對老人比較好呢
Fish and seafood include excuses
魚跟海鮮包含藉口類啊這些
What about eggs, beans, meat?
蛋 豆 肉 肉的話呢
Less red meat but I must say
紅肉要少 但是我必須說一下
We didn't see red meat in our film and television mentality just now
我們剛剛的影視心態裡面都沒有看到紅肉
but it means to say
但是它的意思是說
People who eat less red meat
紅肉吃的少的人
Other people who eat a lot of meat are good
其他的這些肉吃的多的人不錯
But let's analyze these carefully
可是我們仔細進去分析這些
People with fewer lions and less lean meat
獅子也少 瘦肉也少的人
Does he eat red meat? He still does.
他有沒有吃紅肉呢 他還是有的
So I want to emphasize again
所以我再要跟大家強調
I'm not telling you to go back
我不是說叫你們回去
Just eat white meat
就只吃 都是白肉
And then there's just these things, no pork at all
然後就只有這些東西 完全不碰豬肉
i definitely didn't mean that
我絕對不是這個意思
Because our Taiwanese society
因為我們台灣的社會
Pork is a major protein
就是豬肉是一個主要的蛋白質
Its whole suggested implication is that
它的這整個的建議含義就是說
Pork and other proteins should be evenly distributed
豬肉跟其他的蛋白質要平均分配
Not much pork, absolutely not much
豬肉不可多 絕對不可多
but not at all
但是不是要完全沒有
The reason I remind everyone is because
我提醒大家的原因是因為
in taiwanese
在台灣人裡面
Pork is a major source of vitamin B1
豬肉是維生素B1的一個主要的來源
Can't say not to rule it all out
不能不要說全部把它排除
don't go don't do anything
不要走到千萬不要做任何事情
don't go too far
不要做太極端
we're talking about a trend
我們講的是一個趨勢
so understand
這樣了解
OK, so our intervention goal
OK 所以我們設定的介入目標
We are doing the same in the community now
我們現在在社區也這樣做就是
The first time we met an old man
第一個我們碰到一個老人的時候
We're going to estimate his personal calories
我們要估算他的個人的熱量
Then we understand his six categories of allocation
然後我們就了解他的六大類分配
we are going to tell him
我們就要告訴他
and then assign it
然後把它的分配呢
How to adjust the distribution of the four major food categories of his main meal
怎麼樣調整他的主餐的四大類食物的分配
what kind of staple food
就是什麼樣的主食類
what kind of entree
什麼樣的主菜類
what kind of vegetables
怎麼樣的蔬菜
what kind of fruit to match
搭配什麼樣的水果
What about the allocation?
那這個分配呢
we would recommend using some
我們就會建議要用一些
This kind of dinner plate in three-dimensional space
三度空間的這種餐盤
you can easily understand
你可以很容易的了解
Then we ordinary people
那我們一般人的話
you can buy one
你可以一家可以買一個
after understanding
了解之後呢就
Been yours for a while
用了一段時間做你的那個
Quantity is in your head
量就在你的腦子裡
Where do you go out in the future, let alone take it with you
你以後出去哪裡更不用帶著
probably will know
大概會知道一下
That's another way to creatively
那另外就是說要以創意的方式
There are some things you may not normally be used to
有一些東西你可能平常沒有那個習慣
You have to have some imagination and creativity since childhood
你要自小有一些想像力跟創意
mix it in
把它搭配進去
this event we
這個活動我們
Many friends are playing all day long
許多的朋友一天到晚在玩
how to play this match how to match
玩這個怎麼配怎麼配
Then post it on Facebook.
然後就在臉書裡面公佈啊
Then pass it back and forth in LINE
然後LINE裡面傳來傳去
Very interesting
很有意思的
This can be turned into an event
這個可以變成一個活動啦
So at the caring base
所以在關懷據點呢
we tell old people
我們告訴老人
Just say you must press your own heat
就說你一定要按你自己的熱量
eat enough
吃足夠
You have to balance the six high-quality categories
你要均衡的設入優質的六大類
what does this mean
這個意思是什麼呢
That is, every type of food must be eaten
就是每一類食物都要吃到
but no more no less
但是要不多也不少
Of course, the type of food is to be diversified.
那當然食物的種類就是要多樣化
Strive for change
力求變化
Then each category must choose high density
那每一類都要選擇高密度
Let's talk a little bit about the high density
這個高密度的也要稍微講一下
For example, white rice is low density
就是譬如說白飯就是低密度
All shares are high density
全股類就是高密度
It is nutrient dense
它營養密度高
Everyone understands this, it is high density and low density.
這個大家明白吧 就是高密度跟低密度
Over processed is low density, under processed is high density
加工過度就是低密度 不太加工的是高密度
So if you really want to eat healthy, sometimes you have to do it yourself
所以真的要吃健康 有的時候要自己動手做一下
Like me, although I am so busy, I am doing research at Academia Sinica
像我的話 我雖然這麼忙 我在中央研究院研究
I cook it myself for my family every breakfast and every dinner
我每天早餐親自為家人做 每天晚餐
Ready to leave the office at 5:30 and rush home to cook dinner for the whole family
5點半就準備離開辦公室 衝回家做全家人的晚餐
Because I want to make sure I eat healthy and my family eats healthy
因為我要確保我自己吃的健康 我的家人吃的健康
So it's good to do it a little bit
所以稍微動手做一下 也是不錯
good condition for a busy job
很好的一個繁忙工作的一個條件
A glass of plant drink a day
每天一杯植物飲
So this is to say that eating enough calories means eating enough
所以這個講 熱量吃的夠 就是吃的夠
Eat enough calories, eat enough, high-quality big food is good to eat
熱量吃足量 吃的夠 優質的溜大食物 就是吃的好
Last but not least because you might not be able to eat it
最後要吃的巧 因為你可能吃不下去
or when it's time to eat, so the events we do in the community
或什麼時候就要吃的巧 所以我們在社區辦的活動
It is to teach the old man to know his dinner plate, to teach the old man to know whole grains
是教老人認識他的餐盤 教老人認識全股雜糧
we still have tea over there
我們還在那邊做午茶
cultural promotion
文化促進
That is to say, I want him to drink tea again
就是說又想他喝茶
I want him to drink milk again
又想他喝牛奶
Then just make a milk tea culture
那乾脆就做一個奶茶文化
or latte culture
或者是說拿鐵文化
teach them how to make tea
教他們怎麼泡茶
And what are the desserts that go with the tea?
然後泡茶配的點心是什麼呢
It's like dried fruit, lotus fruit, etc.
就是像果乾啊 荷果這種東西
that's very healthy
這樣就非常健康了
Take the milk and lotus fruit that they can't eat
把他們吃不到的奶類跟荷果
eat it all
都把它吃下去
Some old people can't eat the fruits and vegetables
那蔬果有的老人吃不下去
How to eat it creatively
怎麼樣創意的把它吃下去
Of course, most young people will use some
當然一般年輕人就會用一些
Fruit and vegetable juice, yogurt like this, these
果菜汁啊 這樣打優格啊 打這些
The old man may not be able to
那老人不見得可以
What method does the old man use?
老人用什麼方法呢
For example, a situation in our family is
譬如說我們家的一個狀況就是
my mother
我母親
My mother is a hundred years old now
我母親現在一百歲了
she is also very healthy
她身體也非常好
But she does eat less
但是她確實會有吃得比較少的情況
So for example, the day before she
所以譬如說她前一天
If there are vegetables left over from lunch or dinner
如果午餐或晚餐有蔬菜沒有吃完
then we'll collect it
那我們就會把它收集
freeze it well
把它冰好
For example, the next morning
譬如說隔天早上的時候
i'll chop it up
我就會把它剁碎
then with an egg
然後搭配一個蛋
turn into vegetable eggs
就變成蔬菜蛋
Then put it on three sides of her
然後就放在她的三面
For example like this
譬如說這樣子
Then you just make sure he gets the vegetables
那你就是確保他一定蔬菜
will eat
會有吃下去
This is an example
這是舉例啦
What about fruit?
水果的話呢
That is my mother only
就是我母親一天只有
that appetite
那個食慾
fruit that can only be eaten once
只能吃一次的水果
He can't eat in the afternoon and evening
他到下午跟晚上就吃不下
So I must carry a bowl of fruit for him for breakfast
所以我早餐一定幫他背一碗水果
that's it
那到了
if i go home at noon
如果中午我回家的話
I'll pour him a glass
我就會幫他倒一杯
100 percent orange juice
百分之百柳橙汁
put on the table
放在桌上
He will see it when he wakes up at noon
他中午起來就會看到
i'm busy
我很忙著
if i forget
如果我忘記
i go home at night
我晚上回家
Arrive home at half past five
五點半一到家
I'll pour a glass first
就會先倒一杯
100 percent orange juice
百分之百柳橙汁
or grape juice
或者是葡萄汁
put it over there
放在那邊
just ask him to drink first
就請他先喝
then wait until i make dinner
然後再等我做晚餐
that is to say
就是說這種
so-called creativity
就是所謂的創意
if you want
你如果願意的話
what can't be done
什麼事情做不到呢
there is
還有就是
View Breakfast for the Elderly
檢視老年者的早餐
this is very important
這一點非常的重要
because the old and the young
因為老人跟年輕人
The difference is that
不一樣的地方就是說
you young man can
你年輕人可以
I don't eat a meal
我一餐不吃
then i have dinner or lunch
然後我晚餐或中餐
pile of protein
一堆的蛋白質
fill it up
把它補夠了
then my body can take it
那我的身體可以承受
and I always
而且我隨時
My muscle nuclear ability is all in
我的肌肉核檢的能力都在
But the old man did not eat this meal
可是老人的這個一餐沒有吃
He just lost that opportunity to do the synthesis of chicken
他就失去了那個機會做雞肉的合成
Therefore, what is important is that the elderly should eat protein from breakfast
所以講究的是老人從早餐就要吃蛋白質
Meal distribution
三餐分配
It is best to have vegetables, fruits and protein in all three meals
最好是三餐都有蔬菜水果跟蛋白質
ensure the metabolism of his body
確保他身體的代謝
The synthesis of protein chicken is in the best state
蛋白質雞肉的合成是在最好的一個狀態
so we have a moment that is old age breakfast
所以我們有一刻就是老年早餐
Teach them how to eat breakfast and how to match it
教他們怎麼樣吃早餐 怎麼樣搭配
This is a formula we promote in the community
這個是我們在社區裡面推的一個口訣
they still read
他們還有唸出來
I don't know if I click it
我不知道按一下會不會有
thank you all
謝謝大家
awesome
好棒喔
ok this is right there
好 這個就是在那個
I've been working on this project for the past two years
我這兩年正在做這個計畫
The effect will not be known until the end of the year
那個成效要到近年年底才會知道
This weakness of these old people
這些老人的這個衰弱
Is there any progress in all aspects?
各方面有沒有一個進步喔
OK, let me see the time
好 那我看這個時間
It should be almost
應該也是差不多了
So now let's talk about this website
那麼現在就是講一個這個網站
what about this website
這個網站呢
is if people want to know your own
就是如果大家想要知道你自己的
Six categories of book distribution
六大類書分配
you can in google
你可以在Google裡面
I didn't leave the URL
我沒有留網址啦
You are in Google
你就在Google裡面
Hit this Zhongyan Nutrition Information Website
打這個中研營養資訊網
just hit this
就打這上面就好
It will run out like this screen
它就會跑出來這樣子一個畫面
This picture is
這個畫面就
Just fill in your age here
就這邊有這樣填你的年齡
your gender
你的性別
how tall are you
你身高幾公分
how many kilograms
體重多少公斤
and your physical activity
然後你的身體活動量
It has low fever low moderately higher
它有低 燒低 適度更高
make a choice
讓人來做一個選擇
Then here is the description
然後這邊就有描述
who is low
什麼人是低呢
who is low fever
那什麼人是燒低
For example, if you say low
那譬如說低的話
This means most of the time
這個就是說大部分時間
They all sit and study, do homework, and talk
都坐著念書啦做功課啦談話
Watch TV or listen to music part of the time
有部分時間會看電視或欣賞音樂
There is a small process of walking and other calorie consumption for an hour.
便有一個小時的散步等熱量消耗叫小的過程
This one hour, for example, matching
這個一個小時譬如說搭配
For example, if you walk to take the bus
就是譬如說你走路去坐公車
then go home what
然後回家什麼
or walking around the house for about an hour
或者在家裡走來走去大概一個小時
So this is low
所以這個就是低
Then if the fever is low, it means
那麼燒低的話就是說
Except just like this
除了剛剛這個樣子之外
There will be about two hours of walking
還會有約兩小時的步行
Then moderation means that in addition to the above
然後適度就是說除了以上之外
You still have an hour of vigorous work
你還有一個小時的活動強度較強的工作
or such a caloric expenditure
或者是這樣的一個熱量消耗
An hour of activity at a fast pace
一個小時的活動速度快
Calorie-intensive activities
熱量消耗多的活動
For example, if you play ball for an hour
譬如說打球去打了一個鐘頭
this will be moderate
這個就會是適度
but every day
但就是天天喔
If you only call twice a week
如果你一個禮拜只打兩次
you're sick
你就不適了
this is every day
這是天天喔
If it is high, it means high-intensity activities every day.
那高的話就是天天都是高強度活動
You probably look where you belong
你大概看一下自己屬於哪裡
It will do a calculation for you
它就會幫你做一個計算
Here the calculation would say
這邊這個計算就會說
how tall are you for a man
一個男性你多少身高多少
how much weight
多少的體重
What is your BMI approximately?
你的BMI大概是多少
Although you are normal now
你現在雖然是正常
but
但是呢
i would suggest you
我會建議你
It is best to reach BMI22
最好能夠達到BMI22
That is, how much weight
也就是體重多少的情況下
at this weight
那在這樣的體重情況下
Do you need 2099 calories a day
你是需要一天2099大卡
That's about 2100, right?
那就差不多2100嘛對不對
So there are two classes on this side
那所以它這邊有兩個階層
tell you
告訴你說
You're probably somewhere in between
你大概就是介於這兩個的
directly between the two
直接那這兩個之間
What kind of state is it?
是什麼樣一個狀態呢
is that you may eat every day
就是你每天可能是吃
Three or three and a half bowls of rice
三碗或三碗半的飯
divide by three
除以三
just a bowl
就是一碗到
more bowls of rice
一碗又多一點的飯
In this, I hope it means
那這個裡面我希望就是說
at least one bowl is
至少有一碗的是
this
這個
No refinement is what is called
沒有精緻就是所謂的
something like brown rice
糙米那種那種東西
in this way
這樣子
Then you wish you every day
然後呢你每天希望你
have a drink or two
喝一到兩杯
Just a cup and a half of milk
就是一杯半的奶
Then your tofu
然後你的這個豆腐
About six servings of meat and eggs
肉蛋大概六份
The word six copies is the spacer I just mentioned
六份的話就是我剛剛講的隔子
Allocation of six like this
六個這樣子分配
You see it is assigned to three three
你看它分配到三三
Four plates of vegetables
蔬菜要四碟
Three to three and a half servings of fruit
水果三份到三點五份
6 servings of nut seeds
堅果種子六份
This is more difficult to understand
這個比較難以理解
I can tell you about this
這個我可以跟大家講一下
What does it mean
這是什麼意思
Just the nut seed that one of you has a serving of each day
就你中間有一天有一份的堅果種子
What does the remaining five mean?
那剩下五是什麼意思呢
That is, you have five dishes in the four dishes every day
就是你每天四菜裡面有五道菜
it is fried in oil
它是用油炒的
So every day if you
所以你每天如果
You see, four servings of vegetables are already four dishes.
你看你這個蔬菜四份就已經四道菜了
And six servings of bean, fish, meat and eggs
還有豆魚肉蛋六份
there are ten
不是有十個嗎
that is to say
也就是說意思怎麼說
Not every dish is fried with oil
不是每一道菜都讓油炒的
half is good
一半就好
For example, some of my fish today are steamed
譬如說我今天魚有的是蒸的
some are fried
有的是煎的
fried with oil
煎的就有油
steamed without oil
蒸的就沒有油
baked without oil
烤的也沒有油
If the vegetables are cold
蔬菜如果是涼拌的
no oil
沒有油
fried with oil
炒的就有油
so the dish you have is salad
所以你有的菜是沙拉
some dishes are fried
有的菜是炒的
some are hot
有的是燙的
only half of the dish
就是只有一半的菜
whether it is faint
不論是昏菜
Half of it is made of oil
一半的裡面是用油做的就好
But that oil is not a restaurant
但是那個油不是餐廳
Let's go to the restaurant and order a dish
我們去餐廳叫一道菜
Isn't that the whole dish soaked in oil?
不是那個整個菜都泡在油裡嗎
it's not like that
不是那樣的
It's almost the oil level of a buffet
差不多是自助餐的那種油度
I know only half is oily
知道只有一半是有油
Then your oil level is just right.
那你的油量就剛剛好了
some people are healthy
那有一些人就是很健康
No cooking oil
什麼菜都不用油
no no no way
不是不可以也可以
then you can be at your healthiest
那你可能可以達到最健康的狀態
It is your six servings that all use Heguo seeds
就是你這個六份全都用合果種子
The most important thing is that it is possible
最主要是可以的
Every dish of yours is a salad
你每一道菜都是沙拉
Your salad is hot
你這個沙拉那個沙拉燙
this can also
這也可以
So these are where the creativity
所以這些就是創意的地方
good so
好 所以
Speaking of this
講到這邊
I think it's about the same time
我想時間好像是差不多吧
It's about ninety minutes
就是差不多九十分鐘吧
right
是吧
May I
可以嗎
thank you very much
非常謝謝
Ask Professor Han's very informative lecture
發問韓教授的非常豐富的演講
then we now
那我們現在
ask questions
大家發問
If you ask this question, we will give you a copy
這個發問的話我們會給一份
I think it's a magazine for scientists.
我想是科學人的雜誌吧
Thank you all for asking
謝謝大家 謝謝發問
So another one can do
所以另外一位能事
Thank you, Professor Pan, for your in-depth introduction.
謝謝潘教授的深入請出的介紹
I want to ask Professor Pan
想請教潘教授
That is to say, on page 18 of your talk about Bubbles just now
就是說你剛才的講那個泡泡泡的第18頁
After the so-called old people there are weak
那裡的所謂的老人虛弱以後
His activity decreased, his diet decreased
他的活動減少 飲食減少
it's a vicious circle
就是惡性循環的地方
Ask Professor Pan
請教潘教授
It's the English part
就是英文的那一張部分
The professor just mentioned that
那剛才教授有提到就是說
It is hoped to increase the activity and amount of exercise of the elderly
希望說增加老人的活動 運動量
to stimulate his appetite to increase his diet
來促進他的食慾 增加他的飲食
to break the cycle
來打破這個循環
but if say
但是如果說
Our caregivers fall into a myth
我們的照顧者落入了迷思
just say it's because you're unlucky
就說因為你不幸
So I use forced fasting
所以我用強迫斷食
Just use bio fasting, forced fasting
就是用比歐斷斷食 強迫斷食
I cut off so much in a row
我就連斷那麼多的量
People can't break this cycle when it's like this
這樣子的時候人不能打破這個循環
i will ask several questions
我會問好幾個問題
so my first question
所以我先第一個問題
let the professor answer
讓教授來解答
Then I ask the second question
然後我再問第二個問題
I'll ask another question when I get a chance
有機會我再問其他問題
Thanks
謝謝
by force
用強迫的方式
Because I personally don't recommend
因為我個人是不太建議
But none of us did either
但是我們也沒有人做過
It's just that I didn't pay attention to whether there is such a test
就是我沒有去留意有沒有這樣的試驗
what if there is no test
什麼事情如果沒有試驗
It's not good to say it's impossible
就說它不可能也是不太好
But that is to say, if you analyze a state where the elderly cannot eat
但是就是說如果你分析老人吃不下的一個狀態
It eats so little that it can't eat it
它吃的少元是它吃不下
space in its stomach
它的胃部的空間
It doesn't have enough digestion for anything
它的消化力什麼都不夠
so in this case
所以在這種情況下
I believe in forced fasting
我相信強迫斷食
May have some adverse effects
可能會有一些不良效應
so of course i
所以當然我
Because we didn't enter into such a trial
因為我們並沒有進入這樣一個試驗
Can't eat the old man
把老人吃不下
As long as there is a group, it is forced
就分群有一組就是強迫的
so i'm having a hard time
所以我很難
Indeed, your question is really difficult
確實你這個問題真是太困難了
hard to answer
很難回答
but we know that
但是我們知道說
When the old man can't eat
老人他吃不下的時候
If you force him to eat, he will feel uncomfortable
你如果勉強他吃他會難受
Because we're talking about aging now
因為我們現在就是說老化的問題
So the stroke after aging
所以就是說老化以後的中風
what those radar teams
什麼那些雷達隊
Then he will swallow
然後他會吞面吞
But we often meet evildoers and say
但是我們經常會遇到招惡者就說
Then I just have to wait for the break, after the break
那我只要等下斷啊 斷了以後
He can live for several years
他就可以活好幾年啊
just lie there
就躺在那邊
Just lay there and live for several years.
就躺在那邊活好幾年這樣子啊
So the myth here goes like this
所以這裏的迷思這樣子
That's why I asked this question
所以才問這個問題
But what I would suggest is to say
但是我會建議就是說
I just said break
我剛說打破的意思
not in this way
並不是用這種方式
break means
打破的意思就是說
For example, we are in Miaoli Hospital
譬如說我們在苗栗醫院
we'll find out now
我們現在就發現
What's wrong with these old men's reclining strength?
這些老人他的臥力什麼不夠
we designed some
我們就設計了一些
easy exercise for him
簡易的運動給他
he started doing it
他就開始做了
when he first did
當他一開始做的時候
his physical exertion
他的體能消耗
he will start to want to eat
他就會開始想吃東西
I think this is a
我覺得這樣是一個
smarter way
比較聰明的做法
and you
還有就是說你
you change the quality of food
你改變食物的品質
you can design
你可以設計一下
This food is more dance-like
這個食物是比較 dance 一點的
That is to say, it uses a small volume
就是說它用很小的體積
it won't last
它不會撐
eat that nutrition
就把那個營養吃下去
These two methods will
這兩個方法會
I think it will be better
我覺得會比較好
the next page
那下一頁的
The so-called protein American gluten body weight
那個所謂的蛋白質美中筋體重
Calculation standard of the body weight of the American gluten
那美中筋體重的計算標準
based on its current weight
是以它現在的現有體重
Or ideal weight ID28 Liwet
或者是理想體重ID28 Liwet
still have to count the weight
還是要去算進體重
Lin8 Liwet
Lin8 Liwet
dimensional basis to calculate its heavy protein requirement
維基準來算它的重蛋白質需求量
Thanks
謝謝
This is now internationally
這個現在在國際上
Usually the current weight
一般就是用現在的體重
We are also useful Lin8 LiMes
我們也是有用Lin8 LiMes
also counted
也有算過
basically the same one
基本上是同樣的一個
same trend
同樣的一個趨勢
but this is currently
但是這個目前
Currently because it is in this clinical
目前因為它在這個臨床上
more useful method
比較好用的方法
It is directly minus the weight
它就是直接除上體重
I understand that you should fully understand this question
我瞭解你應該是滿理解這個問題
Is you considering Lin8 LiMes
就是你考慮到Lin8 LiMes
body mass may be more important
body mass 可能是比較重要
all good questions
這都很好的問題
Many thanks to Yuan Pan for the report
非常感謝潘源救援的報告
Then I want to say that in this life
那我想說在這個人生
It is the history of birth and disease
就是面臨的生老病史
come here to eat such good food
這來吃這多好的食物
Until the last nine years old and one hundred years old, they are all gone
到最後九歲一百歲也都是走
I want to take advantage of your report
我想趁您做這個報告
do an extended role
做一個延伸的作用
The question until that day is
到那一天的問題就是
stop breathing
停止呼吸
that problem is too big
那個問題太大
I want to extend that
我想延伸就是說
by Namoban
透過Namoban
Scarmorivo
斯加摩利佛講的
there's a world we can go to
有一個世界我們可以去
is the brightest world
是最光明的世界
life is infinite
是壽命是無量
That is to say, the Western Paradise
就是說西方極樂世界
Amitabha
阿彌陀佛
So the theory starts out pretty big
那麼這個理論起起非常龐大
it's not oriental
它不是東教
it is a science
它是一個學問
great knowledge
很大的學問
So Master Xuanzang traveled from Xi'an to India during the Tang Dynasty
那麼玄奘法師在唐朝時代遠從西安走到印度
It took a few years to arrive
走到幾年才到
It took a total of 17 years to return from studying in India
連印度留學回來總共花17年
He has brought back many life theories of Buddhist managers
他已經把很多的佛經理人生理論帶回來了
Like what Wu Liang said, the Diamond Sutra and so on
像吳亮所已經金剛經等等
very great experience
非常偉大的經歷
then these classics
那麼這些經典
Then everyone can solve their own problems
那麼大家可以為了解決自己的問題
Meet your long-term needs
滿足自己最長期的需求
That is to say, watch these classics on TV
就是說好好的在電視上看這些經典
Then there are many mages like Jing Kong mage
那麼有很多法師像靜空法師
Master Haitao came to help us explain
海濤法師來幫我們解釋
Only when a mage explains it can we understand
有法師來解釋我們才了解
There's such a wonderful world we can go to
有這麼好的世界我們可以去
I believe that many people here have learned Amitabha
相信在座已經有很多人學阿密陀佛了
Then another question
那麼另外一個問題就請教
Our research unit is studying this excellent
我們研究單位在研究這個優異
At this time, is there any religion or the Buddhist law I just talked about?
這個時候是不是有把宗教或者我剛講的佛法
Introduced to study how to solve outstanding problems
引進來研究怎麼解決優異有問題
then i will share
那我就共享
If you encounter excellent
如果碰到優異的時候
forget about that now
馬上忘記那件事情
Immediately transform the new realm into
馬上把新的境界轉換成
Amitabha
阿彌陀佛
so new is close
那麼新就是親近
there is no such thing
就沒有那個事
Thank you Amitabha
謝謝阿彌陀佛
ok thank you for sharing
好 謝謝你的分享
let's see if
我們看看有沒有
who has some questions
誰有一些問題
Excuse me
不好意思
That is what the professor just mentioned
那就是剛才教授有提到
proper food and drink
就是適當的食物飲
tea coffee
茶 咖啡
even the so-called wine
甚至說所謂的酒品
suggested by the professor
那個教授建議的
the so-called appropriate amount
所謂的適當量
what is the appropriate amount
適當量是多少
that's it
就是這些的
so-called tea coffee
所謂的茶 咖啡
Even wine, red wine, etc.
甚至酒品 紅酒這些的
the so-called appropriate amount
所謂的適當量
because of coffee
因為咖啡的話
is what we know to say
就是我們知道說
When doing volume
作量的時候
would cause the so-called
會引起所謂的
stop loss stop neglect
阻止流失 阻止疏受
that's again
那又是
other deteriorating part of debilitating
衰弱的另外的惡化的部分
That's why the professor suggested
那所以教授建議的
the so-called appropriate amount
所謂的適當量的部分
Then it's protein
那麽那的話就是蛋白質的
Can't talk about the so-called milk powder, right?
不能當講到說所謂的奶粉對不對
Milk powder is a remanufactured product
奶粉它是屬於再製品
That milk powder and the so-called fresh milk
那奶粉和所謂的鮮奶
It's in making this about our nutrition
它在製成就對我們的營養的這個
Is there a difference in the scenery difference?
風景差異上面是不是有所差異
Thanks
謝謝
because we are today
因為我們今天
discuss this issue
探討這個問題喔
it has a bit of what it should say
它有一點應該怎麼講
is that it is a political
就是它是一個時政
Because it this food is a
因為它這個食品是一個
very complicated thing
非常複雜的一個東西
it can't be like a
它不能像一個
so-called basic research
所謂基礎研究
That is to say one thing at a time
就是說一次探討一個東西
because it is very complicated
因為它是非常複雜
So we usually when making recommendations
所以我們通常在做建議的時候
from this information
就是從這個資料
see what can be seen
看到可以看到的範圍
let's make suggestions
我們來做建議
that is to say it is not easy
也就是說它不容易
so-called heterodyne
所謂的外差
Or extend up and down
或者是往上延伸往下延伸
Then when I was looking at our profile
那我在看我們的資料的時候
I find
我發現
The so-called group that eats a lot like tea
所謂那個像茶飲吃得多的那一組
in this way
這樣子
it is about
它就是大約是
so the coffee is over there
那麼那個咖啡在那邊
Taiwanese people eat less coffee after all
台灣人畢竟咖啡吃得少
Its relevance is like this
它的相關度是這樣的
coffee is usually
咖啡通常都是
These chitons are just two or three cups a week
這些赤頓都是一個禮拜兩三杯而已
But the tea is almost drunk to a cup a day
但是茶都差不多快喝到一天一杯
So now I can say that
所以我現在可以說就是
Based on our current political observation
以我們這個時政的這個觀察
the state of this crowd
這個人群的狀態下
Looks like a cup of tea a day would be nice
看起來一天一杯茶是不錯的
and I think the main effect
而且我覺得那主要的功效
probably from tea
可能是來自茶
because it is a pattern
因為它是一個Pattern
it is relevant
它就是相關
But you will see that there is still less coffee in that range
可是你會看到那個範圍咖啡還是少
I don't know if Taiwanese really
我不知道台灣人如果真的
When Westerners drink so much coffee
像西方人喝到那麼多咖啡的時候
what will happen
會怎麼樣
So I must say that when I was talking about this thing today
所以我必須說我今天在講這個東西的時候
I think it depends on your personal physique
我會覺得說要依你個人的體質
But if I want to promote this thing
但是我如果要把這個東西推廣的話
I will focus on tea
我是會著重在茶
Because it is more tea
因為它的就是茶比較多
this is your first question
這是你的第一個問題
as for a little more
至於再多一點
I believe there is no problem
我相信也沒有問題
as long as you are drinking
只要你在喝的時候
I still feel that the body can adapt
都還覺得身體可以適應
Like some people the coffee is good though
像有一些人咖啡雖然是不錯
but some people can't drink coffee
但是有一些人不能喝咖啡
can't drink
不能喝
basically
基本上
just because it's a
就是因為這是一個
how to say
怎麼講
This is Observation
這是Observation
is a human
是一個人類的
Natural Experiments
Natural Experiments
a thing of nature experiment
天然試驗的一個東西
So we can't go beyond it too much
所以我們不能超越它範圍太多
so this is the first question
所以這是第一個問題嘛
I just forgot the second one
第二個我剛剛一下忘了
milk powder
奶粉
Yeah
對對對
this is indeed
這個確實
A fresh milk has this structure of this protein
一個鮮奶它的這個蛋白質的這個結構
with milk powder
跟奶粉
because milk powder
因為奶粉經過
put moisture like this
把水分這樣子
evaporate
蒸發掉
Its structure is indeed different
它的結構確實是不一樣的
but i must say
不過我必須說
I because I am studying nutrition training
我因為我是學營養學訓練
We usually focus on nutrition
我們比較通常著重在營養
The problem with this structure involves
那這個結構的問題涉及到
This immune allergy
這個免疫過敏這塊
It's not my major
是比較不是我的專業
but we found
但是我們發現
That is to say, in nutrition
就是說在營養學這塊
milk powder and fresh milk
奶粉跟鮮奶
It seems that there is not much difference
好像是沒有太大的差異的
that is
就是說
For protein intake
針對像蛋白質的攝取量啊
calcium intake
鈣質的攝取量啊
So if it is beyond this range
所以如果說是超越這個範圍
of
的
When it comes to allergies, it's not my field.
到過敏這塊就不是我的領域了
But I feel there is no difference in nutrition
但是我感覺上對營養是沒有差別的
You said you have to walk steadily, right?
你說走路要穩定是吧
oh
哦
Weak feet will fall
腳沒力走路會跌倒
In fact, I believe there are many reasons
其實相信有很多的原因
But if you're talking about what we're talking about today
但是如果您講的就是我們今天講的
this debilitating word of encouragement
這個衰弱症激勵的話
that big problem
那大問題
OK, what we are talking about today is the issue of motivation
OK 我們今天講的就是激勵的這個問題
Because you see the protein I talked about today
因為你看我今天講那個蛋白質
There is also protein, which is a raw material for muscle synthesis
還有蛋白質它是提供那個肌肉合成的一個原料
Then we mentioned that fruits and vegetables are anti-inflammatory
那麼我們講到蔬果蔬果是抗發炎
We all know why old people talk to young people
大家知道老人為什麼跟年輕人
Eat the same protein but your muscle synthesis doesn't
吃同樣的蛋白質但你的肌肉合成就沒有呢
It's because your body is in a state of inflammation
就是因為你的身體處於一種發炎的狀態
Your synthesis side is weaker
你的合成的這邊的能力比較弱
Therefore, there must be antioxidant
所以一定要有在抗氧化
It will be better if it is provided together with protein
跟蛋白質同時提供的情況下會比較好
But if a person is already weak enough
但是如果一個人已經是肌力不夠的時候
It must be paired with exercise
那一定是要搭配運動的
is that you have to match some breaks
就是你要搭配一些斷裂
so in this
所以在這個
We're in the middle of this Selary study
我們在這個塞拉瑞症的研究中間
We have four types of sports
我們有四種類型的運動
The middle one is muscle strength
中間一個就是肌力
Main resistance exercise, strength training and stretching exercise
主抗運動練肌力有伸展的運動
There are soft exercises and aerobic
有柔軟的運動還有有氧
all four
四種都有
Then there are upper and lower limbs
然後還有上肢跟下肢
There are such sports
都有這樣的運動
so if you
所以如果你
Your weakness is not due to structural problems
你的衰弱不是因為結構的問題
or neurological problems
或者是神經的問題
If the muscles are weak
就是肌肉比較軟弱的話
You should start to practice the underhand
你應該是去開始練習下盤
some movement in the lower body
下盤的一些運動
including things like squats
包含像深蹲這些
Then ask a sports coach
然後請教一下運動教練
can be practiced
是可以練的
But light nutrition is not enough
但是光性營養不夠
big problem you tell him
大問題你跟他說
Any question
還有問題嗎
yes
是
please
請
black tea
茶有紅茶
green tea
綠茶
yes
是
There are black tea and green tea, right?
茶有紅茶跟綠茶對不對
What about green tea?
那綠茶有什麼紅茶
pure green tea
純綠茶
and light green tea
還有淺綠茶
that black tea
那個紅茶
some are grape tea
有些是葡萄茶
So black tea is better?
那到底是紅茶比較好呢
Is green tea better?
還是綠茶比較好呢
In terms of nutrition and moisture
從營養水分來講
no difference
沒有差別
because
因為
because i should say the same
因為我也應該這樣說
It is because of our research
就是因為我們這種研究
This is an epidemiological study
這個是一種流行病學研究
If you really want me to divide it so finely
你如果真的要我分得那麼細
I have no way
我也沒有辦法
So I see from our data that
所以我就以我們的數據來看是
no difference
沒有差別
But I believe there must be some
但是我相信一定應該會有一些
slight difference
些微的差異
But that difference is
但是那個差異是
I can't answer today
今天我沒辦法回答的
there's still something like that
還是有一點就是那種
vitamin c problem
維他命C的問題
So why isn't vitamin C a problem?
那維他命C為什麼不是一個問題呢
It is because people in Taiwan
就是因為在台灣地區的人
Your Designated Amount of Vitamin C
你的維他命C的設計量
It has reached two or three hundred times your daily demand
已經高達到你一天需求量了兩三百倍
you know we do research
你知道我們做調查都知道
just doesn't matter
就是沒有關係
high is okay
高是沒有關係
but that means we are
但意思就是我們是
go go go
已經go go go
us
我們
But that doesn't mean
可是這並不表示說
You can't take vitamin C supplements
你不可以吃維他命C supplements
it's two different things
這是兩回事
So I think the vitamin C thing is relatively small
所以我是覺得那個維他命C的事情比較小
Then the advantages of this check
那麼這個查的優點
Definitely not only in this flesh-wrestling disease
絕對不是只有在這個摔肉症
Like our market and do some other research
像我們市場還有做一些別的研究
like ever done i did npc bni
像曾經做過我做過NPC BNI
Diet Patterns for BNI
BNI的飲食型態
An intermediate protective factor is to check
中間一個保護的因素就是查
Then I have the impression that all kinds of checks are protected
那我印象中也是各種查都保護
Cha is really a very good
查真的是一個非常好的
Various chronic life
各種慢性命
It has a preventive effect
它都有防治的一個效果
contains cancer
包含癌症
the teacher has another question
老師還有一個問題
usually when drinking tea
通常喝茶的時候
drink tea like me
像我喝茶
Because I have been drinking tea for about twenty years
因為我喝茶喝了一個二十年左右
I don't dare to drink tea so far
喝茶目前為止我不太敢喝
why
為什麼呢
After drinking, there will often be a phenomenon of willingness
喝完之後就會經常產生願意的現象
Is it the same with drinking coffee?
那喝咖啡也是是不是一樣呢
No coffee should be no
不會 咖啡應該是不會
Coffee should be an opposite in this piece
咖啡應該是一個相反在這一塊
Because there are some other minerals in coffee
因為咖啡裡面還有一些其他的礦物質
it will help you have a bowel movement
它是會幫助你排便的
So I don't want to be constipated by tea
所以我不想因為茶這個便祕現象
we are other
我們是其他
we don't have this experience
我們是沒有這個經驗
Maybe this is a condition of a constitution that varies from person to person
可能這是因人而異的一個體質的一個狀況
yes
對啊
there is one behind
後面有一個
Excuse me
請問一下
You have contributed here says
你這裡有貢獻說
The fourth said the anti-inflammatory food
第四個說那個抗發炎食物
I want to ask about the sweets
我想請問說那吃甜的東西
Will it make that body inflamed?
會不會讓那個身體發炎
Sweets are an inflammatory food
甜食是一個發炎性食物
Yes
是的
What are anti-inflammatory foods
抗發炎食物是什麼
Anti-inflammatory foods we usually are
抗發炎食物我們通常就是
fruits and vegetables
蔬果
It is absolutely anti-inflammatory
它是絕對抗發炎的
then again
那麼再來就是
like fish
像是魚
picture
像
this piece of oil
油的這一塊
fat part
油脂部分
that is, every type of food
就是每一類食物都
can talk like this
都可以去這樣談
I just said that the first one is vegetables and fruits
剛剛講第一個就是蔬菜水果
anti-inflammatory
抗發炎
So what about fat?
那麼油脂的話呢就分
saturation
飽和
Unsaturated
不飽和
and
跟
this
這個
just how to say
就是怎麼講
As for the oil, it tends to be plant-based
油脂這一塊的話是傾向於植物
vegetable oil
植物油
Then
然後
with fish oil
跟魚油這兩款
But what about vegetable oil and fish oil?
然後但是植物油跟魚油呢
Is fish oil more anti-inflammatory
是魚油比較抗發炎
But fish oil probably can't eat too much like this
但是魚油大概這樣也不能吃太多
mean to say
意思就是說
In terms of general sneezing oil
以一般的噴嚏用油來講
we lean towards vegetable oil
我們傾向於植物油
But if the vegetable oil says
但是植物油裡面如果說
olive oil
橄欖油
canola oil
芥花油
and these soybean oils
和這些黃豆油來講
In other words, olive oil is the only advantage
的話呢就是橄欖油是只要再優勢
Another advantage because it is more antioxidant
再優勢因為它比較抗氧化
What about soybean oil?
那麼黃豆油這些東西呢
If you use stir-fried salad
如果你是以炒的涼拌的
The use of these methods is also ok
的這些方式使用也是ok
But that soybean oil
但是那個黃豆油
sunflower oil these if used at high temperature
葵花油這些如果用到高溫
it is less inflammatory
它就比較不就比較會致發炎
It's a little bit complicated, it's a little bit complicated
是有一點複雜啦稍微有點複雜
Good cleanser oils are very inflammatory
好清化油是非常致發炎的
absolutely can't eat
絕對不能吃
Now Qinghuayou government has legislated
現在清化油政府已經立法
take it out of food
要把它從食物中拿掉
It has been in law for almost three years
已經立法快三年
It should be three years
應該要三年就是那個
That is, after three years, high-speed manufacturers
就是高速廠商在三年後
A complete ban is probably the closest
要全面禁止大概就是最近
Three years ago, it was enacted that no cleaning oil should be used
三年前就已經立法不可有清化油
to the limit of hell
要地獄相當的限度
Then I see I don't know yet
那我看我不知道還沒有
What did not expect is basically oil
什麼沒有想到基本上就是油
Vegetables and fruits are the most important
跟蔬果是最重要的
Teacher, I beg
老師我求一下
During your research, you mentioned that it was
您這一邊研究的時候有提到說是
body mass and muscle mass
身體質量跟肌肉量
The amount of brittle falls in old age of boys is much more serious than that of girls
男生的老年摔脆量比女生嚴重很多
yes
是
What is the mechanism that causes men to have this situation?
那是怎樣的機制會造成男性有這個情形
OK
OK
we all know men
我們都知道男性
That is to say, his aging process is actually
就是說他的老化過程其實就是
The aging process that has been going on since growing up is in progress
從長成之後就一直的老化過程就在進行中
What about women?
那麼女性的話呢
Generally speaking, it is women because of the protective effect of female hormones
一般說起來就是女性因為有女性荷爾蒙的保護作用
So before a woman's menopause
所以在女性停經之前
Basically, various chronic disease indicators are in a very good state
基本上各種慢性病指標都處於非常好的狀態
Women don't see this chronic disease take off until after menopause
女性是在停經之後這個慢性病才開始起飛
So women can be said to be later than men
所以女性可以說比男性晚了
It can be said that it has been like this for decades
可以說幾十年這樣子
So when we look at various indicators, we can see such a phenomenon
所以我們看各種指標都可以看到這樣的一個現象
For example, female obesity
譬如說女性肥胖
Women's gut ratings all take off after the age of fifty
女性的膽固準評 全部都在五十歲以後才開始起飛
Then later rushed to be taller than boys
然後後來衝到比男生都高
Men have rushed to a peak after the age of seventy and all come down
男性已經衝到一個高峰七十歲以後都下來了
But that's down because of aging, not because of getting better
但是下來那個是因為老化 並不是因為變好了
So basically it's a female hormone protection
所以基本上就是個女性荷爾蒙的保護中
should be the biggest reason
應該是一個最大的原因
Hello, Teacher Pan, your main thing is nutrition, right?
潘老師好 你主公的是營養吧
Then let me ask you about a nutritional therapy and nutritional repair in the future.
那我請教一下 未來的一個營養療法跟營養修護
What is the progress in China and what breakthroughs have been made?
在國內的進展是怎麼樣 有哪一些方面的突破成果
Your problem is very, very big
你這個問題非常非常的大
feel a little bit about breakthrough we can
對 突破 覺得有一點 我們可以
Maybe we can chat a bit later
或許我們等一下可以稍微閒談一下
Because nutrition is really, really complicated
因為營養學真的非常的複雜
There are many other aspects. What I am talking about today is the positive aspects of old age.
還有很多的面向 我今天講的是老年正
so i'm having a hard time answering
所以我有點難以回答
because of baby nutrition
因為有嬰兒營養
nutrition for pregnant women
有孕婦營養
Have nutrition for the elderly
有老年營養
Chronic Disease Nutrition
慢性病營養
Disease prevention and treatment with cancer
有育癌的疾病防治
and disease treatment
還有疾病的治療
many facets
好多面向
so i can't answer right now
所以我現在一下難以回答
do you have any specific questions
你有沒有什麼特定的問題
Teacher Pan
潘老師
You seem to be on the heart side
你好像是對心臟方面
full of a heart weary even
滿有一個心肝疲慰甚至
no large system
無大系統
A repair and therapy for noodles
做面的一個修復跟療法
most importantly
最主要是
Presentation of one of its research results
它的一個研究成果的呈現
If you come to the country where you are from now
來到目前來源的國內的話
what better way
有什麼比較好的一個方式
for example
比如說
like my heart
比如說我心臟的話
There is a problem caused by
有問題是由
A functional underground of the pretend line
假裝線的一個機能地下
The function of the pretend line is underground
假裝線的機能地下是
I am nourishing myself
我本身在營養
Absorptive capacity
吸收能力
a factor of the missing part
缺少部分的一個因素
Does it affect the heart?
影響到心臟嗎
even affect the kidneys
甚至會影響到腎臟
Yes or no
是不是
nutritional therapy
這些營養療法
Current Domestic Research
目前的國內的研究
is there any progress
有進展到哪裡嗎
i don't know
我比較不清楚
terribly sorry
很抱歉
because
因為
assume this
假設是這個
that pseudogland
那個假狀腺
because we generally
因為我們一般
adenopathy in the largest
最大中的腺臟病
it involves
它涉及的就是
canned bean disease
罐狀豆麥腺臟病
Then you just
那您剛剛這種
is the so-called
是所謂的
called secondary
叫做二級
that is because
就是說是因為
caused by other diseases
其他疾病所引起的
It actually has a lot to do with nutrition
它其實跟營養學的關係比較遠
Relatively far
比較遠
because I do nutrition
因為我做的是營養學
close like a can
關上像罐狀
that arterial
那個動脈的
this heart disease
這個心臟病
is the largest
是最大中
it involves
它涉及的就是
diet
飲食
Fat
脂肪
Metabolic abnormalities
代謝異常
with diabetes
跟糖尿病
this metabolic abnormality
的這個代謝異常
The main thing is this
最主要是這個
cause me in this
在這個原因引起我
But the one you just said
可是您剛剛講的那個
not my research scope
不是我研究範圍
sorry sorry
抱歉抱歉
see if there is anything else
看還有沒有什麼
other questions
其他的問題
and you just mentioned that
然後你剛剛提到說是那個
when boys
男生的時候
when the whole recession
那個整個衰退的時候
waning from the start
一開始就開始衰退
but i used to
但是我以往
The information given to us is that the girl is after menopause
給我們的資料是說是女生在停經以後
The speed of the entire recession will grow very fast
在整個衰退的速度會長非常的快
But just now when the teacher made this information
但是剛剛老師這一個資料的時候
When the girl was at the time of the decaying speed
女生的時候那個衰退的速度的時候
Much slower than boys
比男生的時候還慢很多
What direction is this looking at?
這個是有看什麼方向
One of the worst things women do have is osteoporosis
女性確實有一個最糟的就是骨質疏鬆
Women lose bone very quickly after menopause
女性在停經之後會骨質疏鬆的速度非常的快
She is indeed presenting an immediate drop
她確實是呈現一個立刻下降
This is one of the most serious problems for women
就這個是女性最嚴重的一個問題
men won't
男性不會
males are slowly declining
男性是緩慢的下降
But what I just talked about is the other aspects
可是我剛剛講的就是其他的面向
especially metabolic like diabetes
特別就是代謝像糖尿病
like a heart attack
像心臟病
like high blood pressure
像高血壓
This piece of women starts after menopause
這一塊女性是在停經後才開始
deterioration
惡化
But a woman is actually saying that she has a long time ahead
但是女性其實就等於說她前面有很長的時間
It doesn't matter if the protection period starts at the beginning
保護期如果一開始二話沒關係
It is very important for women to stop menstruation
女性很重要一點就在停經的時候
Make drastic lifestyle adjustments now
立刻做極大的生活型態調整
It will be pressed back
就一下就會壓回來了
So it's fine for women too
所以對女性來說也蠻好
It's because you suddenly discovered how my body changed
就是你突然發現我怎麼一下身體變化
If something is wrong, change immediately
發現不對了立刻大幅改變
If you want a big change, you can suppress it
要很大的改變就可以把它壓下來
So yes lifestyle therapy has its uses
所以是生活型態療法是有它的用處
Excuse me, teacher, you just kept emphasizing
請問老師你剛剛一直強調要
All Protein Milk Eggs
都是蛋白質 奶類 蛋類
But when we eat protein
可是蛋白質我們吃下去的時候
acid in the stomach
到胃裡面經過強酸
PH3 is all denatured
PH3的這個都變性了
Can it be used by our body again?
還能再被我們身體利用嗎
Transgender broke or what?
變性壞掉還是怎麼樣
is not like this
是不會這樣子
It is actually a process of digestion
它其實是個消化的過程
What we eat is protein
就是我們吃進去的是蛋白質
Proteins are many amino acids
蛋白質是許多的胺基酸
formed long sword
結成的長劍
So the long acid digestion in the stomach
所以到胃部的這個長酸的這個消化
is very important
是非常重要
because in that situation
因為在那個情況之下
break down some proteins
一些蛋白質分解沒
will put this long chain
會把這個長鏈的
The so-called ecology cut it off
所謂的生態把它切斷
cut into tiny amino acids
切斷成了小小的胺基酸
we can absorb
我們才能吸收
Without this action
如果沒有這個動作的話
In fact, those proteins can't be absorbed
其實那些蛋白質也沒有辦法吸收
so it's not like you might think
所以並不是像您想像
Say it breaks, it ain't breaks
說它會破壞,它不是破壞
its destruction is called
它那個破壞只是叫做
should be called decomposition
應該叫分解
break down from large molecules to small molecules
從大分子分解成小分子
So we can take advantage of the absorbed
所以我們可以利用吸收進去之後
recombine in our body
再在我們身體裡重新組合
Become an ecological long chain
成為生態長鏈
in the necessary position
在必要的位置
emerge with the necessary structure
以必要的結構出現
that transgender is not
那個變性不是
like that us
就像那個我們
eggs to fry
雞蛋去煎
become hard
就變成硬掉了
that is transgender
那就是變性
the same with stomach acid
那同樣的碰到胃酸
also transgender
也是變性
that ruined the whole
那是破壞了整個
no no no
不是不是這樣
That's what it means to change sex
就是說它變性是這個意思
That is, it is in an animal or plant body
就是說它在一個動物體或植物體
form of existence
的形態存在
Then after you pass through the Lord
然後你經過主以後
already transsexual
就已經變性了
For example, protein white is liquid
譬如說蛋白質白是液態的
Mainly will become solid
主要是會變固態的
The three-dimensional space of its structure changes
它的結構的三度空間改變
The three-dimensional space has changed
三度空間改變而已
Then after you enter this body
然後你進到這個身體裡之後呢
No matter how it is three-dimensional space
不管它三度空間怎麼樣
i cut it off
我都把它切斷
It's the protein breaker cup
就是那個蛋白分解杯
cut it all off
都把它切斷
Cut it all into one tiny unit
切斷就變成全部變成一個小小的單位
So whether transgender or not
所以不論是變性與否
just eat your eggs
就你生的蛋吃下去
Or eat your already solid egg
或者是你已經固態的蛋吃下去
It looks the same until it is decomposed
它到最後分解完都長一個樣子
They are all small one by one
都是小小的一顆一顆一顆的
just one by one
就一個一個單位的
Then the inside grows long enough to absorb it
然後內部長到把它吸收進去
and its body is back where it should be
然後它的身體重新在該有的位置
like muscles
譬如說肌肉啦
Or do the necessary synthesis of each part
或者是各部位去做該有的合成
so not a problem
所以不是一個問題
that lady
那位女士
to the back
對後面
Okay, then there is another classmate behind you
好你然後後面還有一位同學
Miss
女士
Hello Dr. Ann
安博士你好
I have seen it said here
我在這邊有看到說
Has published more than 300 academic papers
曾經發表過300多篇的學術論文
Among them, you are focusing on the diet and genetic inheritance of metabolic diseases in the elderly
其中你是著重在新藏學館代謝級老年疾病的飲食與遺傳自殷
here factor
這邊因子
Where can we see your paper
請問我們可以在哪裡看到你這篇論文
All of our papers are written in English
我們這些論文都是用英文寫的
Internationally
在國際上
so
所以
what kind of journal
什麼樣的期刊上面
various periodicals
各式各樣的期刊
So I don't know about your little show We have a place in academia called
所以我不曉得你小表演我們學術界有一個地方叫
P-POP-MAD P-U-B-M-E-D
P-POP-MAD P-U-B-M-E-D
this
這個
You type P-U-B-M-E-D in Google
你在Google裡面打P-U-B-M-E-D
you will go in
你就會進去
Then you call Pan Wenhan
然後你就打潘文函
My English name
我的英文名字
my english name may be
我的英文名字可能
W-E-N
W-E-N
you just call my name
你就打我的名字
You can if you can type my name in Chinese on Google
你可以如果你可以用打在Google打中文我的名字的話
you can see my english name
你就可以看到我的英文名字
you type my name in
你把我名字一打進去
All my papers will come out
我所有論文都會出來
that he
那他
But I'm afraid you don't understand
可是怕您看不懂啊
it's all in english
就是都是英文的
right
對
I want to focus on what is the special topic of this article
我再想著重這一篇的特殊的一個題目是什麼
his
他的
For example, there is a
譬如說有一個
You said it was today, right?
你說今天的是吧
no
不是
that is
就是
In more than 300 articles, he
三百多篇裡面他
Emphasis on this article
著重的這一篇
OK
OK
This doesn't seem to be the focus
這個好像不是著重這個
He said it was this series, this series
他說是這一系列這一系列的
this series
這一系列
right
對
this kind
這種
theme
主題啦
right
對
There are various papers
有各式各樣的論文
Thanks
謝謝
I think
我覺得
Take his question and ask it by the way
接他的問題順便問下去
Now the question you just focused on is
那現在你剛剛著重的問題就是說
Nutrition for Cardiovascular Metabolism
心臟血管代謝的營養
then ask
那請教一下
Where is the hottest direction right now
現在最熱門的方向是在哪裡
Cardiovascular
心臟血管
his
他的
for example
譬如說
people with coronary artery disease
有冠狀動脈疾病的人
in terms of diet
在飲食方面
what is the latest theory
最新的理論是什麼
because it is not said recently
因為最近不是說
Sometimes Cholesterol Is Not All That Causes
有時候膽固醇並不是完全是造成
Causes of hardening of the arteries of the heart
心臟血管硬化的原因
The latest theory
現在最新的理論
In fact, there are many
其實也是很多面向
Let me put it this way, I know you may be quite interested in cholesterol.
那這樣講我知道您可能對膽固醇這一塊還蠻有興趣的
high blood cholesterol
血液中膽固醇偏高
it cures heart disease
它是會治心臟病
And that's basically narrowing this canister artery.
那主要就是讓這個罐狀動脈狹窄
That theory has not been disproved until now.
那這個理論到現在都沒有推翻
still exist
都還依然存在
Now the latest controversy is that
那現在最近的爭議是說
can you eat eggs
你吃蛋可不可以
high blood cholesterol
血液中的膽固醇偏高
It will definitely cure cardiovascular disease
是一定會治心臟血管疾病
Increased risk of cardiovascular disease
會讓心臟血管疾病的風險提升
it's ok
這是確定的
The problem is that eating eggs
問題是說吃蛋
Will it increase blood cholesterol
會不會讓血液中的膽固醇提升
yes the problem is here
是問題是在這裡
What about this
那對於這個來講的話呢
A correct statement is that it should be
一個正確的說法是應該是這樣
That is to say, the cholesterol content of the egg itself
就是說蛋本身的膽固醇含量
Affects the blood to a moderate extent
會影響血液中的程度不高
the degree is not high
程度是不高的
The most important factor affecting blood cholesterol
最主要的影響血液中膽固醇的因素
is saturated fatty acid
是飽和脂肪酸
that is, the butter
也就是那些牛油
For example, eating butter
譬如說吃butter
And red meat, pork fat
還有紅肉 豬肉的肥肉
There is CTS oil, coconut oil
還有就是中旅油 椰子油
These oils and the backlash just mentioned
這些油 還有就剛剛講的反噬
These are the ones that cause the blood to be high
是這些會造成血液的偏高
So why did you talk about eggs before and don't talk about eggs now?
那麼為什麼以前會講蛋 現在不講蛋呢
It's just that the diet of human beings in the past is a little different from what it is now
就是以前人類的飲食跟現在有一點不一樣
in the previous time and space
在以前那個時空下
This egg has a greater impact
這個蛋的影響比較大
Now the time-space egg has less influence
現在這個時空蛋的影響減小了
So the same research is repeated and redone
所以同樣的研究一直重複做就重做
Now slowly find that the impact of eggs is getting smaller
現在慢慢發現蛋的影響變小了
so it will follow
所以它就會跟
plus Americans
再加上美國人
Because this suggestion is from the United States
因為這個建議是來自美國
Cholesterol drops across the U.S.
美國人全民的膽固醇量都下降了
Since the United States of America has changed the recommendation to say
因為美國的國家就改變了建議說
Eating eggs is not that serious
吃蛋其實沒那麼嚴重
The most important thing is to protect the fat
最重要的還是保護脂肪
still say so
還是這樣說
But this is for ordinary people
但是這是對一般人
If you are a person with already high cholesterol in Cholesterolology
如果您是膽固醇學中膽固醇已經偏高的人
However, it is still necessary to minimize
但依然是要盡量減少
or should you say
或者是你應該是說這樣
if you find you eat eggs
你如果發現你吃蛋
you can test yourself
你可以自己做個檢驗
just go up
就上去的話
should be reduced
就是應該要減少
do you understand
這樣明白嗎
it points to common people's advice
它分一般人的建議
It is still different from the patient's suggestion
跟病人的建議還是不同的
so i don't know what else
所以我不知道還有
other salary
其他的薪資方面
Because everyone does a lot of different research
因為每一個人都做很多不同的研究
For example, what I am currently doing
譬如說我個人目前在做的
There are two relatively new
有兩塊是比較新的
I'm talking about a mineral
就是我探討一種礦物質
minerals are beautiful
礦物質是叫美
The protective effect of this beauty on heart diseases
這個美對於心臟血緣疾病的保護作用
I'm currently discussing
我最近在探討
Actually I have published a
其實我已經發表一篇
Journal of the American Academy of Clinical Nutrition
在美國臨床營養學會雜誌
I help this patient
我幫這個病人
patients who have already had a stroke
就已經得了中風的病人
I scan his beauty every day
我每天給他掃量的美
A month later his stroke recovery was better than no one
一個月之後他的中風復原比沒有的人
is twice as good
就是好兩倍
It has been published here
那這邊已經發表了
Well, I actually found that this beauty may affect blood flow
那其實我發現這個美可能會影響到血流
So I'm doing a study recently which is
所以我最近在做一個研究就是
head and beauty
頭與美
See if it affects the blood flow rate
看看會不會影響血流速度
that affects this
那影響這個
If it affects the blood flow velocity from the neck to the brain
如果影響到頸部到腦部的血流速度
We now have to go further
我們現在還要進一步探討
Will it affect dementia
會不會影響到失智
For example, this is my current
譬如說這個就是我目前
a new study being done
在做的一個新的研究
But I dare not tell you now
但是我現在不敢跟你講
I'm not done yet
我還沒做完呢
Another research we are doing is
另外一個我們在做的研究就是
After making oil to fry it
做油去給它炸了之後
fried food
就是炸物
Will it affect a variety of different diseases
會不會影響到各式各樣的不同的疾病
Then we found that
那我們發現就是說
May be some fried it's ok
可能是有一些油炸了沒關係
some fried
有一些油炸了不行
So if this result comes out in the future
那所以如果這個結果將來出來
i will
我就會
just maybe for example
就是可能譬如說
How do you tell the public when you hold a press conference?
開記者招待會兒怎麼告訴大眾說
OK if you want fried food
OK如果你要吃炸物
you must use this oil for frying
你必須用這個油來炸
But fried food no matter what
但是炸物不管怎麼樣
just good fried
就是好的油炸
There will also be some problems, so I will explain them clearly to you.
也是也會有一些問題就是會跟大家講清楚
Which oil can be fried and which oil can not be fried
哪個油可以炸哪個油可以不可以炸
Then its best to fry as much as you can eat in a week
然後炸最好一個禮拜最多只能吃多少
That's another research I'm doing
那這是我另外在做的一個研究
That of course means that if it is fried for too long
那當然就是說如果炸的過炸過久過度
This means that qualitative variability is another possible problem
這代表質變性也是另外一個可能的問題
right
對
We just had a problem here
我們那個剛才這邊有個問題
there is a question
有一個問題
there is a classmate
有一個同學
right
對
I want to ask Teacher Pan about that
我想要請問潘老師那個
Why do some elderly people's feet are particularly prone to cramp
為什麼有些老人的腳會特別容易抽筋
Does it have anything to do with diet?
那跟飲食有關係嗎
The problem of cramping is also
抽筋這個問題也是
In fact, sometimes a symptom
其實有的時候一個症狀
Actually very
其實非常的
It should be said that non-specific is
應該講non-specific就是
Usually we are talking about causal inference
通常我們在講因果推論
means that A will cause B
是說A會導致B
But is B just because of A
但是會B是不是就因為A
it's hard to say
這個很難講
Your question now is a little bit
您現在這個問題是有點講
For example, it's not the same as virology.
譬如說可是跟病毒學不一樣
Hepatitis B Virus
病毒學說B型肝炎病毒
can cause hepatitis B
會導致B肝
if you have hepatitis B
如果你有B肝
You are the hepatitis B virus
你就是B型肝炎病毒
But now the cramp problem is A, B, C, D, E
可是現在這個抽筋這個問題就是有A、B、C、D、E
There's a whole bunch of them that can give you a cramp
有一大堆都會讓人抽筋
so i'm having a hard time answering
所以我有點困難回答
But if we talk about the diet
但是如果說飲食的這一塊的話
often
經常是
caused by electrolyte imbalance
電解質不平衡所造成的
calcium for example
譬如說鈣
For example, beauty
譬如說美
For example, A
譬如說甲
but i can't decide
但是我不能講定
it should probably mean
就可能應該是說
Nutritionally related is electrolyte imbalance
營養學相關是電解質不平衡
Imbalance can cause cramps in the elderly
不平衡會造成老人抽筋
And you see athletes running
還有你看運動員跑步
Does the long hair cramp at the end?
長毛跑到最後是不是也抽筋
That's also an electrolyte imbalance.
那也是一個電解質不平衡的問題
Okay, we'll have this question later
好我們這個問題在後面
Teacher Pan, I want to ask for advice
潘老師我想請教
That's what I saw mentioned in different places
就是我看到不同地方提到說
can't drink too much milk
不能多喝牛奶
Because of the hormone he contains
因為他所含的這個荷爾蒙
can cause cancer
會導致癌症
And this is because the milk in the process of releasing oxygen
而這又是因為牛奶在釋氧過程中
given antibiotics
被施打抗生素
Another saying is that
另外一個有一個說法是說
The order in which we eat protein foods is linked to weight control
我們吃蛋白質食物的次序會跟體重控制有關
Protein should be eaten first or after
吃飯的時候應該要先吃蛋白質或後吃
Can affect weight control
會影響體重控制
Please help me with this question
這段問題請教您
OK
OK
The first one is about the problem of not being able to eat this kind of milk
第一個就是有關於這個奶類不能吃的問題
This is indeed very popular on the Internet
這是確實是網路上非常流傳
We often even I often receive emails to see such problems
我們經常連我都常常收到email看到這樣的問題
From the standpoint of our nutritionists
以我們營養學家的立場來講
We think it's a stigma against milk
我們覺得這是一個對於牛奶的污名化
it's a pity
就是非常的可惜
a very good food
一個非常好的食物
The result is stigmatized like this
結果被這樣污名化
I don't understand where these things come from
不明白這些東西是哪裡來的
But I can also imagine
但是我也可以想見說
Why do ordinary people easily accept such a concept
一般人為什麼會容易接受這樣的一個概念
just because milk has a problem
就是因為牛奶有一個問題
so-called lactose intolerance
就是所謂的乳糖不耐
If you are lactose intolerant
如果你有乳糖不耐的時候
words in the short term
在短期之內的話
You do have some lactose in the upgrade
你確實因為有一些乳糖在升級
Lactose cannot be metabolized in the body
乳糖在身體裡沒有辦法代謝
may cause some
可能會造成一些
a symptom of diarrhea
腹瀉的一個現象
even some bad microbes
甚至一些不良的微生
growth of intestinal flora
就是腸道菌群的生長
make you uncomfortable
讓你會不舒服
like flatulence or something
譬如說脹氣或什麼什麼
will definitely have this problem
會絕對是有這個問題
so when you eat it you don't feel well
所以當你吃下去不舒服
Then when paired with these rumors on the Internet
然後再搭配這些網路上的傳聞的時候
you'll feel it's right
你就會覺得它是對的
So cause this phenomenon
所以造成這樣現象
But if we look at big data
但是我們如果看大數據
For example, if you look at big data
譬如你看大數據
We still have a lot of data like nutritional surveys
我們像營養調查還有很多的數據
Let's analyze domestic people who drink milk
我們去分析國內的有喝牛奶的人
His health is better
他的健康狀況就是比較好
And he's a protein
還有他就是一種蛋白質
if there is a milk drinker
如果有喝牛奶的人
he is usually less fat
他通常比較不會胖
He is less prone to some metabolic syndrome
他比較不容易有一些代謝症候群
So he actually if you analyze the data
所以他事實上如果你分析數據
he's all right
他是一點問題都沒有的
But ordinary people experience
但是一般人就經驗到
Seeing this makes me feel uncomfortable
看到這種又經驗到自己不舒服
So his problem is because of lactose intolerance
所以他的問題是因為乳糖不耐症
Then lactose intolerance can be overcome
那麼乳糖不耐症是可以克服的
His method of overcoming is
他的克服方法就是
you start with a small amount
你開始就是少量
like me personally for a while
像我個人也有一段時間
just not busy
就是沒有很忙
We are too busy to pay attention to this matter
我們工作的忙碌沒有注意這個事
So then I can't drink milk
所以後來我就不能喝牛奶
So then I because I'm a nutritionist myself
所以後來我因為我自己是一個營養學家
I said I made it look like this
我說我都搞成這樣子像話嘛
So I started cultivating my own lactose-digesting enzymes
所以我就開始培養自己的乳糖消化酶
how to do that
那是怎麼做呢
That is to say, today you make a cup of tea, for example
就是說你今天你泡一個譬如說茶飲
I will let it go today
我今天就放
I like to use milk powder
我是喜歡用奶粉啦
because it is more convenient
因為它比較方便
Just put a soup and a pool of powdered tea milk powder
放一湯一池的茶粉茶的奶粉而已
You'll be fine if you drink it
喝下去就沒事啊
Then two o'clock the next day
然後隔天就兩時啊
drink like this for a week
這樣喝個一個禮拜
i can take two hours
我可以承擔兩時
next week at three o'clock
下禮拜就三時
then four o'clock
然後再四時
no problem
就沒問題了
Just one time to cultivate it like this
只要一次這樣把它培養起來
you can drink later
你以後就可以喝了
This is such a point of view
這是這樣的一個觀點
So our nutritionists' dietary guidelines in Taiwan
所以我們營養學家在台灣的飲食指南
We recommend a day alone
我們就建議一個人一天
one to two cups
一到兩杯
that's one and a half cups
就是一點五杯
but i have to tell you
但是我必須跟大家講
That's what I'm working on recently
就是我最近在做一個議題就是
that is climate change
那個就是氣候變遷
Then let's read the latest article I recently read
那我們在我最近讀到最新的文章
started to talk about an issue
有開始講到一個議題
This is an idea of sacrificing the small self for the sake of the big self
這個就是為了大我 犧牲小我的一種想法
That is to say, if there is not enough food in the world in the future,
就是說 如果將來全球的食物不夠的時候
What kind of food shall we eat
那我們要吃什麼樣的一個食物
it maintains health
它既維持健康
And then to ensure global food security
然後又能保障全球的食物安全
everyone has food
就大家都有飯吃
that such a food
那這樣的一個食物
Just be less animalistic
就是要少動物性
less animal
動物性要偏少
But it's not about eating bad food
但是並不是說吃難吃的食物
Then when I was reading these papers
那我就在讀這些論文的時候
Discover their recommendations intermediate for milk
發現他們的建議中間對於奶類
Do you want to see how good cheese Westerners eat?
你想看西方人吃多好的起司
Pizza Burger Milk Coffee
披薩 漢堡 牛奶 咖啡
Good milk is there
都好奶類在那
but they say
但是他們就說
in the future they will wish to say
他們未來會希望說
That's the amount of a glass of milk a day
一天就是一杯牛奶的這個量
just fine
就好
This is for environmental protection
這個是考慮到環保
When considering this climate change
考慮到這個氣候變遷的時候
Let me tell you about this latest trend
我就跟大家講一下這個最新的一個趨勢
Is that glass of milk good for health?
那一杯奶是不是可以達到健康
It must be possible
一定也可以的
because you are in that situation
因為你在那樣狀況下
you will go with other food
你就會去搭配其他的食物
Can soy milk replace milk
狀況豆漿可以取代牛奶嗎
soy milk
豆漿
In our current dietary guidelines
目前我們現在的飲食指南裡面
If you follow the current dietary guidelines when eating
你如果按照現在的飲食指南在吃的時候
it won't work
它是不行的
Because we plan it as your calcium
因為我們把它規劃成你的鈣質
And your B complex and some minerals
還有你的B群還有一些礦物質
Like armor and beauty are derived from milk
像甲跟美都是來自奶類
Then soybeans
那麼黃豆的話
Definitely delivers the same amount of protein
絕對可以提供同樣的蛋白質量
But the calcium in soybeans
但是黃豆中間的鈣質
Much less than these B groups
跟這些B群都少得多
So in the future if we want to do this
所以未來我們如果要這樣做的話
So we often learn as we do
所以我們常常我們一樣學會
One more topic to talk about is
要再講一個議題就是
with added soymilk
就是有添加的豆漿
It's this soy milk that adds some
就是這個豆漿把它添加了一些
Even food rich in group B is fine.
就是B群豐富的食物也好
Or add vitamin calcium and D
或者是維他命鈣質跟D加進去
This can be considered in the future
這是將來可以考慮的
It's just that we have had some conversations with manufacturers
只是說我們跟廠商有做一些對話
The food world they have so far had no will
食品界他們到目前還沒有意願
launch this thing
推出這個東西
So in the future we will see what kind of method to use
所以將來要看看用什麼樣一個方式
Encourage the so-called matching with milk
鼓勵會有所謂的跟奶類搭配
It is soy milk with exactly the same nutritional value
就是營養價值完全相同的豆漿
Our countrymen also like to drink
我們國人也蠻喜歡喝的
So I think this is a direction we will work hard in the future.
所以我覺得這個是未來我們會去努力的一個方向
ok i think it's about time
好 我想時間差不多
So let me give you a preview of the next self-thought feast
所以我先預告一下下一場的自想宴
It was the lecture given by President Zhu Jiahua Ke Puye on May 28
是5月28號朱家華院長柯普也講座
Wang Baoguan Banquet Room, the Center of Environmental Change
是環境變遷的中心的王寶冠宴室
He used to be the director of the center
他過去是中心的主任
The secret of the coming and going storm in the long wind
長標風中自來往暴風雨的秘密
Everyone is welcome to sign up
歡迎大家藉事前往報名
Thanks again Professor Pan Honghuan
再次謝謝潘宏環教授
Thank you.
Thank you.